Hello, and welcome to a new video in the ZAP Chat series.
And this is going to be a video about a new feature in the new ZAP release, 2.14, and
it's called ZAPit.
And this time I'm actually joined by Yiannis.
Hello.
So usually I stick to these videos, I keep technical.
But on some interviews I've done, I have explained my security origin story.
And what happened was, I'll keep it very short, there was a pentest that did not go as well
as expected on one of my services, and I knew it was going badly after I came in one hour
into the pentest.
Only to find one of the pentesters logged in as myself, super user, having cracked the
single sign-on system for the whole company.
Now why is that relevant?
Because that was the first time I met Yiannis, who was the pentester who logged in, who
cracked the single sign-on service.
So Yiannis, I don't think I've had a chance to publicly thank you for ruining my week
in 2009, but also more importantly, starting my security journey, which led to ZAP.
So thank you very much.
Thank you for your patience and being part of this cyber community.
Little did I know we're going to be here a few years later, right, discussing the amazing
tool that you've put together with the team.
Myself and the team, exactly.
So do you want to give us a quick introduction to yourself?
Yeah, sure.
Just keeping it short, my name is Yiannis Papouasoglou.
I have contributed to a number of web application relating standards and activities.
And currently, one of the things that I've really enjoyed is getting
back into contributing to ZAPit and seeing some of the great work, Simon,
that you've been doing with the team and the code and how much of a tool, how like how well established
is ZAPit within the webapp sec community.
Congratulations to you and the team on that.
Thank you.
So, I mean, you got back in touch with me a few weeks ago, wasn't it?
It wasn't long ago.
And you came to me with this idea and I just thought, oh, I like this.
So give us an overview.
What is ZAPit?
What's the idea?
Well, I got back into web application security after having served as chief information security
and you know joining a number of senior echelons of management as CISO and really looked at the
state of the tool set that we're using and was not happy with it.
ZAPit being a prime good example, but most of the tools out there, if you download any
pentesting image, you're bog standard
web app toolset is not really that good
and my motivation in reaching out to you was, well, I know that you have solved this problem.
We'll talk a little bit about what this is in a second.
But we haven't made it simple for the web app sec community, not just penetration testers,
but also developers, also product owners, people that end up owning a website they've
inherited.
We have not made their life simple in terms of understanding what they're up against.
In terms of a web app that they've been handed either to test or they've inherited and they
need to look after it.
So the basic premise of ZAPit started with what is the maximum we can get out in terms
of a response, single request response, to figure out what we're up against.
Either Monday morning, the pentester is starting the web app test or somebody has inherited
an application and they're trying to see what they're up against, trying to get a feel of
it.
And what really motivated me was people were still using the old tool set because, you
know, great tools, but a bit dated, things like Paros and Nikto and similar, which, you
know, are very good.
But at the same time, you know, the world has moved on a little bit.
It's 2023 and we need to, you know, come up to speed with what it is that actually the
needs out there to figure out quickly and promptly what you're up against.
In terms of a web application.
That's the motivation.
And that's what got us here.
And as you said, you quite well have a little bit of that.
How was it received on your side, Simon?
Really good.
I mean, this was something that really spoke to me, particularly when I was at Mozilla.
I had responsibility for the web applications behind Firefox.
And they're all too many times when you find out about a new web app.
And sometimes you'd find out about them early in design stage.
Sometimes you'd find out when they're in staging.
Often you'd find out from some sort of marketing release and you go, oh, I don't know about
this.
So, you know, what you need to do, you know, there's lots of ways you find about new applications.
Obviously you can try and find out who's behind it, talk to them.
But while you're trying to find that out, I just want to know as much as possible, as
quickly as possible about this URL.
Is it something, does it raise loads of red flags or is it, okay, no one, you know, I
don't feel so bad about this.
So, you know, by the time you get on the phone or on Zoom or on Slack or whatever, you've
kind of got an initial impression of that application.
And that's what I could imagine myself using this for back in, you know, when I was doing
that job.
Indeed.
And I think those are the, that's the primary use case.
Those are the three use cases.
So Pentest is trying to figure out.
Yeah.
What they're up against.
Somebody who's looking after an application that maybe shouldn't have reached production,
but somehow magically is already in production.
That's a second use case.
And then also somebody trying to figure out just the baseline real quickly of what the
app is doing.
Right.
So I think that's enough talking let's let's demo.
Yeah, absolutely.
Let's go for it.
Yes, indeed.
So first of all, let's start with ZAPit itself and the great 2.14 Release.
Yeah.
What are you going to be showing us?
Right.
One of the, so obviously I've got ZAP installed and a lot of you watching this these videos
will have, but if you haven't what you can do is you can actually run it via Docker,
or if you're on Kali, you can do it that way.
The thing is, this is actually a command line option.
So there's no GUI at the moment.
It's just a command line.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm going to run ZAP and I'm going to do the ZAP statement.
And then I'm going to run a command line.
And then I'm going to run the command line.
Yeah.
And then I'm going to run ZAP stable from software security project slash ZAP stable.
I've pulled this already just to speed things up and don't worry about copying down these
commands.
We're going to write a blog post about this.
So all the commands will be in there.
So you don't have to desperately try and copy what I'm doing, but that will basically put
me in a bash shell in the ZAP stable Docker image.
Now, if I do ./zap.sh -h, just to just run the help and it will have
set up the root of the standard directory.
As you'll see, we've got a whole load of command line options.
And lower down here, we'll see ZAPit target URL from a quick reconnaissance scan and also
says the minus command option must be used.
So let me just.
So what I'm going to do is minus command and then -zapit
and https://www.example.com
and you know often we say with ZAP, you should only be testing ZAP against applications you
have permission to test.
In this case, we are doing no attacking at all.
You can see we just made one request there.
So it's a standard HTTP or HTTPS request.
And so we can see that and we'll show you some examples of redirect some it. And you can see how long the
request took the response code the response size no cookies in the quest response and then
technology it's not available because we actually need another add-on for that
so let me install that so minus command and then we want to do addoninstall
right number of l's. So Simon while you do that tell us a little bit about the wappanalyzer
add-on what does it do? Yeah so wappanalyzer is a third party product it's actually
just been taken close source and luckily someone else has forked it and is now maintaining
it it really looks at requests and responses typically responses and works out what technology
is behind the web applications it's really useful and also i'm going to install the pscan
rules beta so we have a set a particular stable image we have a set of release quality scan rules
both active scan rules and passive scan rules p scan rules and passive ones we in the stable
image we don't include the beta ones so i'm going to install the passive scan beta rules
there are also alpha rules as well so could install those and that just gives us more
information there's just extra things but these rules are not quite as stable and well tested
as the release quality ones. So you basically have to install the two add-ons wappanalyzer and p
for passive scan rules beta and because it's in beta it's not included by default that's why you
have to install that excellent. I will just do add-on update now i this will actually do nothing
here but add-on update always tricky with a live demo add yeah add-on
update now i'm not expecting this to do anything because we've only just released the stable
release but obviously we release it once a week sorry once a month so if there are any updates
in between we'd miss out on those i said add on update complete check complete nothing else
installed so we're now we're looking good and what i'm going to do is i'm just going to go back
and run ZAPit against example.com again. And now we'll see a little bit more about the tech.
Yeah and here we go so again we still see the request coming in and here's the technology so
we can see amazon ecs, amazon web services, azure, azure cdn and docker and i think we've got so
what we're showing now is the alerts now these are alerts raised by the passive scan rules
and we can have high, medium, low and informational and you know you have to you shouldn't just
believe these and go okay
there's been a particular alert therefore there's a vulnerability therefore i raise it via bug bounty
or whatever try and get some money it'll be you know always you should always double check these
things and just because there's an alert you know it might then it might well be the company's
decided we know about this and it's not a problem we do not want to enable this particular security
control so you know these these information for you just give you an idea of what's going on
and we also give you root page stats so
you can see things like the content type number of html tags, number of links forms and number of
input fields and remember this is on the very first page. So that's the information from example.com
which is not a particularly interesting application actually so Yiannis what else should we test?
Let's have a look at something that's going to give us a lot of verbosity..
Shall we start with twitter.com? Okay.
So let's have a look at Twitter. So Twitter is going to be interesting in a number of ways
first and foremost in terms of what does it allow as oh there we are as a number of sub
resources and specific items where wildcards are being used you see the medium CSP content
security policy wildcard director they actually need that in order to allow
video to be functioning right so going back to simon's quote it's not about taking a medium risk
finding from ZAPit and then including it in your pentest report it needs further analysis and
triage. What i like about the response here is that it under you know one second 565 milliseconds,
i'm able to figure out what technology Twitter is still using right, on the new leadership i'm able
to figure out real quickly what it is that they're doing and what they're doing and what they're doing
in terms of the web application setup so if we scroll a little bit further down Simon you see
that we've got a number of script javascripts and a number of lows as well correct in terms of cross
domain
javascripts happening again needed functionality the way that Twitter is set up and then also to
Simon's point i can see what i'm dealing with in terms of html tags, forms, links so a lot of tags
very little
forms one input field straight away we know roughly what what we're up against. And there's
also informational modern web application so a lot of security tools are much more effective
with traditional web applications now we've done quite a lot of work with ZAP to make it handle
modern web applications better there's still more work to do but one of the things that
does is actually tries to detect modern web applications so we can actually choose then to
use the ajax spider instead of the traditional spider or as well as the traditional spider.
So there's lots of so you know we can see that ZAP has detected this you know there's a lot
of really useful information here. Indeed, indeed you know what you're up against in a very short
time right normally this would take a number of other tools some of which are not maintained in
order to figure out what what you're up against now you have all that information in one page
on monday morning as you start start starting your next
web application test. And we see things like response cookies and you know and if you see
multiple requests and responses for redirects you'll see the cookies go across so you see a lot
of information and.. Another one? Yeah let's have another one. Let's go for something that returns
a 404 so having looked at the websites and actually one of the ways that we tested this was
we took the top 1000 websites for one list or another it doesn't matter which one and we saw that type of
responses we we got back. Running against all of them. Yes, yes absolutely so fonts.googleapis.com
is on the top 100 it's basically by default a website that returns a 404 an error back nothing
comes back but there is something of value that will come back from the response that we're going
to see here there we are we see the 404 now what's interesting straight away even though i have a 404,
i can see http/3 is beeing used as a technology
of course this is going to have to be investigated further and actually assess whether or not http/3
is being used in terms of you know sending a request that supports not only http/1, 1.1, 2 but
3 and seeing what response you get back but we got a hint that something that is future future
technology is being supported on the googleapis.com on the fonts sorry googleapis.com.
Now one thing one thing i think is interesting here is content security policy header not set.
Now we often see these on 404s and there was quite recently a case of sql injection attack on a 404
impact. Yes! So you know and quite a few people you know i've had cases before gone to developers
and said look you haven't got CSP on your on your error pages and they've gone do we really need it
and i've tried to convince them they do but i haven't had good examples of you know this is a
this is why you really need it and now we have a good example why you should really have you
know we've got CSP on the rest of your site you probably want it on your for on your error pages
as well. Yeah absolutely and i have a big b in my bonnet about sql injection still being around
because after being in the corporate world for for more than 10 years i set up my second
company kyberna and one of the services of course that we had to offer right was pentesting, because
that's part of the bread and butter of what infosec companies do and we started off with 2
pentests one on the dotnet framework 4.5 and one on java jakarta 10 you know your standard
enterprise just both had sql injection i couldn't believe it and this was you know this was last
year effectively when we when we started the company and it's like i phoned up needless to
say Simon i phoned some of the original authors that we wrote OWASP testing guide with
and had a big long rant about how come sql injection is still around. That is crazy.
So what i'm going to test next then? Let's have a look at so we did Twitter shall we have a look
at the BBC website? Yeah let's and i'm going to do http just to.. Very often in many circles
the BBC is used as for example when you're connecting to a wireless network
and you don't have the certificate for ssl the BBC is used in http as the website that is being served.
Traditionally to test connectivity and we see a lot of responses come back
and you have i know Simon you have a favorite on this page i don't want to take.. I do go back to
the front so you can actually see we've got two redirects here because we request to bbc.com
http so that gets redirected to https and then we yeah then we get redirected to
https://www.bbc.com so and then as we scroll down we'll see lots of interesting things
the one i particularly like is suspicious comments "fixme".
We get interesting information here. Absolutely and again this is you know something that could
have a little bit of meat on the bone or it could be just you know something that's
involving some javascript component that really makes no difference in terms of exploitation or
vulnerabilities but straight away in under a second you're able to deal with the 302s
the redirects and then you're able to just have a view of what you're up against
or just a single request and response really like that feature. Right well i think we're actually
running out of time on my zoom unfortunately so better wrap this up quite quickly. Thank you
very much for that introduction to ZAPit and the suggestion now i mean one thing we do want to
do is we've got we've got we'd love to hear about people using this and how you get on with
it and you've got any suggestions because we've got lots of extra, we've had lots of thoughts on
things we could do so you know, we've got we could have some html or pdf reports, we could
actually have an option to have a longer scan where we kick off the spider would you want to
know how many end points there are?
These things will take longer but there's lots and lots of things we could do but we don't have that many people
working on ZAP and there's a million things we want to do so we also only want to do the things
that are really effective that people really want and really want to use so please try this out
and let us know how you get on. So that's it thank you very much and subscribe to the channel and let
us know what you think about it and what else you'd like us to cover thank you very much! Thank you!