Hello and welcome to another ZAP Chat video. Once again, I am joined with by Yiannis.
Hello.
So this week we are going to be covering automation. What I want to do is give an
introduction to ZAP automation, kind of explain what all the options are and why
you might want to use them. So what I do is I'm going to share my screen straight
away because what I'll do is switch over to my browser and show you the ZAP
website and if you go to documentation then go to automate then you will see
make that a little bit can I zoom in on that remember the keys yeah so there
you'll see the list of automation options.
Now that's not all there is to it otherwise we'd kind of have to stop here so what I want
to do is kind of go through these options and explain what they're useful for actually
demo most demo most of them as well but one thing I think we've got a lot of options and
one of the reasons is because we've got ZAP is has a lot of functionality and when you're
automating ZAP we found out that some people want some very simple options and some people
want some very complicated things and therefore what we're looking at is trying to have a balance
between ease of use and flexibility and functionality. So for the demo I'm actually
going to run I'm running the weekly so it's the latest weekly and let me find a so I will just
start up the ZAP GUI just to try and make a little bit of a point and what I want to do is one of the
options here is to show all of the tabs and you can now see there's
Lots of tabs.. Yeah.. so if you think each one of those tabs is equivalent to a tool within ZAP
so ZAP is it's almost like an IDE or you could say it's an integrated hacking environment so
it is very complex and it's complex because it has to do hard things finding security vulnerabilities
in web applications is hard and you know do well you have to do you really need a manual pentester
like Yiannis for example but so we have lots of options for manual pentesters but what we try
and do is we try and make as many of these options automatable as possible and if I'll just go and
have a look at the options screen here and go through you'll see there are lots and lots of
options. Configuration Parameters, right? Yeah, so this means ZAP is really tunable but it also means that if you're running ZAP from
the command line there's a huge amount of things you could configure so it's how do we actually
make that usable while still being helpful. So the very first one we took on that list
switch back
is ZAPit. So Yiannis you know about ZAPit don't you? Do you want to give a quick summary?
One or two things the whole idea is that we issue one request get one response back now it might be
a 302 when we direct etc but the page that we get back we analyze to the fullest possible extent
and you get a feel of what application you're up against by looking at a single view a single page
the question is have you zapped your website that's where ZAPit comes from and we can
see now Simon that it's a command line option correct? It is yeah we don't actually have a
GUI option for it so I'm going to run it from the command line and actually what I'll do is I'm going
to show you this really exciting test page that I've created and it says it's a very simple page
absolutely nothing. HTML - I haven't seen that in years. Yeah so the reason I've done this is because I
want to demo all of these options and if we had a proper website there it would take too long.
You know full scans of using ZAP take a while because you know there's a lot of functionality
to test. So what I'm do is I'm going to run ZAP from the command line I'm using a I'm using
the minus dir option because then that keeps ZAP's configuration separate and it keeps separate from
my dev environment where I'm doing all sorts of horrible things. I'm starting ZAP on a different
port because I've got tomcat on 8080 and I don't want to clash with that. Minus command because
I'm doing this on the command line minus ZAPit and the target url and we'll see very quickly that
it's made one request and it got a 200. I haven't actually got the wappalizer add-on installed so
it can't tell you what technology involved. Five alerts it's found on the root page it's found
eight html tags no fields. So this is and you know if you're interested in this ZAPit scan
then
we actually recorded another video on it so keep going watch that for more details.
The idea as Yiannis said it's a very quick tell me about this stuff. So great but it's not really
good for finding you know you're not going to find a cross-site scripting vulnerabilities
all of these things SQL injection that's not what ZAPit is for. So yeah this is simple and effective
but of limited use or limited functionality.
Now the next one is the
quick start command line and that is actually a little bit similar but it does a bit
more. Now.. One more exciting? So if I just do actually let me get back to get those options
still and just do minus h then that should give me all of the command line options. Now we don't
actually list these anywhere on the website because we have a set of command line options
that are available in the core and then every single
add-on can add their own command line options if they need to.
So the options you've got available will depend on which add-ons you've got installed.
Now if you ever scroll down somewhere you will see we've actually got
this quick url quick out and quick progress. So what I'm going to do is
make sure I can see what I'm doing now. So I'm actually going to change this to quick url.
And run it again.
Now a few things here are going to be slightly different right even though we're scanning a
single page we've actually triggered the spider. This is not the AJAX spider this is the
like a good old basic spider.. Exactly!.. either in beforehand.
Yeah it's traditional spider and what you'll see is we've actually dumped out
an xml report on the command line.
How helpful is this? I don't know but you'll see we actually have this quick out file name
so you can actually choose to put the report to a file which is probably more useful and you can
actually choose whether you have the standard html json markdown or xml results based on the file
extension. We've also got a quick progress option and this just kind of shows you how far it's
getting along. So this is useful it's
give you more information than ZAPit. But depending on the website could take a lot longer.
But as Yannis said it uses traditional spider there's no option for the AJAX spider and no
other options really that's about it. So it is very quick or quick to use not necessarily quick
to run and has limited functionality.
So what's next? We have these docker package scans and we have
GitHub actions which I'll kind of treat them as the same because the GitHub actions
are just wrappers around the docker package scans. And the docker package scans actually provide
quite a bit more functionality. So we have this docker user guide and we have three different
types of scan. We have the baseline scan, the full scan and the API scan. So let me just go and
kick these off. What I'll do is... It's getting more interesting here now we have the
option to specify what type of scan we're going to get back right? Yeah exactly. So
I'm going to run the baseline scan and so I'm running docker and I'm going to use the
zap weekly and can you can you guess what's going to happen here?
It's a trick question by the way. So first of all you'll see we're actually using the automation
framework..I don't think that's the answer were looking for.
No I'm just waiting to see whether it because I'm expecting this to fail can you tell me why it's going to fail? You're passing a URL..the port is right..
The Problem is local Host because the package scans run in docker and I'm running my Tomcat on locally and
the package scans run in docker
and I'm
running my tomcat on locally and so docker cannot actually access local host yes so this is actually
a docker problem or feature if you like it is not something that is under our control
so what we need to do is we need to find out what URL is accessible to docker and there's various
all will depend on your operating system but on the Mac i can actually find out my local URL there
and i can then actually use that and place this in. Now if your target app is actually in another
docker container on the same machine again you'll have similar problems but there are different ways
around that we've got more details on the website and i'll just mention again so the fact we're
using the automation framework we are actually porting or we're migrating the package scans
to use of the automation framework because it actually provides more flexibility and means
it's easier for us to maintain. So one thing you'll notice is we've actually found a total of 33 URLs
which is surprising because it is just one page on the app and you can actually see all of the
passive scan rules that ZAP has run and that have passed. So what what happens with the package scans
is they will by default use all of the scan rules you have available. So if you've just got the
the release quality ones then those will just be those but you've got
beta status and alpha status they will be used as well by default.
So that's an important point and Simon
just real quickly where have we specified in the command line options that this is a baseline scan
if you don't mind just showing us that? It was actually there so zapbaseline.py so it's a python
file it's a python python script. Very important right so all the baseline scans as part of the
automation sorry all the scans as part of the automation framework are specified in a python
format and you can see them in the command line. In the package scans so these are the package scans which
happens to use the automation framework.
Correct yeah yep. Yeah exactly and what you'll see is we then have these warnings and we're actually
warning on things on slash docs so that's why we're actually running the spider on the from
the root of the directory rather from the url we actually specified and that's for historical
reasons and a few different cases we found where it causes a lot of problems not doing that.
So we found a whole load of things and we got
you'll see down here we've got different things like fail-new, fail-inpro inprog in progress,
warn-new, warn-inprog, ignore and pass so there's actually quite a lot more things going on here.
I switch back and we'll have a look at the docker user guide that kind of explains
various you know that's kind of an overview but if we go into the baseline scan we'll see that
there's actually a lot of we have a lot of options here and you can actually see all of those so if i
go just put baseline minus h then that should give the same list um so one thing you can do
is you can specify a configuration file and this actually allows you to change which of the rules
apply or which of them fail or you or warn or ignore. So we scroll down here
we'll see an example configuration file and what you can do you can actually there's an option to
generate a configuration file from the command line as well and by default everything is warn
and you can then edit this file it's just a text file tab separated and you can change that to fail
or ignore and then that will change how the package scan works... Right, right. ..and then you'll
see we've got options for reporting again
similar to the quick start option it's the standard html, markdown xml or json reports so
we can't specify any format you like there's a limit there we've got an option to include
passive scan rules and there's an option to include the AJAX spider as well and various
other things so you've got delays and there's quite a few extra options and if you actually
you can actually specify a context file and if you do that then you can also specify a user
but you have to configure this context file separately probably via ZAP.
So it's very important to tie this into the earlier if you like basic functionality let's
say you've ZAPit right ideally you want to be checking during ZAPit what the milliseconds
are of the request response if you're going to be specifying any timeouts in the advanced scan
and generally you want to be ready to go from a baseline perspective before you get into the
even more advanced scan and then you want to be ready to go from a baseline perspective
before you get into the more advanced stuff that simon's about to show us. Yeah and one thing we've
got is we actually have limits on how you know how long to spied for example because the baseline is
actually um so when i was working at mozilla we configured the baseline scan to run on every
pull request on some of our repos. So this will actually finish within a few within a couple
of minutes so it's something that you can use within CI/CD.
So one of the
options we have is so we've got the API scan and that i'm not going to demo because
by example that doesn't have an API definition but this supports OpenAPI, Soap and GraphQL
and we'll probably have postman support coming very soon hopefully.
So but the other one then is the full scan so what i'll do is go back to here and then
run the full scan
and this shouldn't take much longer because it's only that single page
but and it we will not be a even though we'll be spidering from the root we will not
be attacking everything so we'll only be attacking the the example page that i've generated
but if i switch back then you'll see the full scan has very similar options
and in fact the configuration file can also include the active scan rules as well as the
passive scan rules. So and again the the minus a option will include the alpha active and passive
scan rules the package scans actually always include the beta scan rules again for historical
purposes. Very important, yeah. So we're expecting a lot more verbosity and a lot more output
with this type of scan right? Normally yes, but in this particular case we're not expecting it
because there's not much functionality there, but this is we're actually attacking the application
and this is one reason why i didn't want to use example.com because i don't have permission to
attack example.com something like the baseline scan is absolutely fine, but the the full scan
is is not acceptable you shouldn't be doing that if you don't have permission.
Yeah and something on time real quickly i i remember when i was training our red team
and they would have a real big problem in scaling in terms of time how they attacked an application
and that would be because you know just imagine that you have x number of fields available right
and you need to check them all for SQL injection well that's one check right but if you have
multiple checks cross-site scripting and so on then that time grows exponentially and that
exponential growth
means that of course you're going to be twiddling your thumbs expecting for the scan to complete
but now it's an advanced scan it's not a baseline scan and that means that the time that you need
to cater for that needs to be sufficient, right? So word of warning there going from changing
baseline scan to something much more advanced also implies that you're going to have an
exponential growth in the time of scanning let alone the spidering that will come before it, right?
Exactly and you'll see here we've got a lot more passes
so we've got a you know we've actually 131 which is so we're running a lot more rules here
and we're running the active scan rules as well as the passive ones. So it's doing a lot more
and if you're running against a real application this will take significantly longer but this is
where you will actually find the interesting things like cross-site scripting and SQL injection.
I said this is where we're actually attacking so you do need to have permission to attack
the application you're targeting. So i'm not gonna so the docker i'm sorry the GitHub actions
are essentially the same as the docker package scans they are using the docker package scans
but you also have the option to raise issues on the relevant repos as well so they'll add a little
bit more functionality there. So what i want to do now is actually create an automation framework
plan so there are various ways of doing that but the easiest one is actually by running ZAP
and so let's just so i'm gonna start up ZAP.
And while that loads up what exactly is a plan Simon? So an automation plan is a set of jobs.
So that has a lot of functionality and we've kind of distilled those into a set of jobs
that we think will be most useful in automation and what you need to do is go to the automation tab
which is hidden by default and what you can do is then if that..
We have various buttons down here and we have an option to create a new plan.
Now you have to specify context so this works quite well if you've actually done some manual
testing first which i haven't done
and you'll see what effect that has and we've got profiles here and you can see
this is the list of jobs so this is all of the jobs available to me
based on what i've got installed and if you actually go to the documentation you will see
a list of all the jobs that are available. So i'm there may be well be some jobs that aren't
available to me because i don't have those relevant add-ons installed but online you will
have the full list.
Now, you can choose a custom profile, in which case you can choose whichever jobs you want,
but I want to do a full scan, so I will save that, and you'll see we now have this list of jobs down
here, and they've got a status. Now, just for kicks, I will run that, and you'll see immediately
I get an error, and you've switched to the output tab. You'll see no URLs defined in any of the
contexts. I haven't told the plan what to do. Right, what to do, yeah. Yeah, so what I can do is
we can double click on any of these things, and we can then actually modify stuff. So what I want is
I want my URL, and you can put any number of URLs in here, and it will include everything else,
and you can actually include, exclude, and technology configurations. You can't actually
configure the authentication for the context here, even though this is actually something
that the automation framework supports, if the GUI hasn't been updated yet.
Another thing I will do is I will change the report, because I think I'll go for traditional
PDF, and I will display the report when it runs.
Oh, the other thing is I will
take the AJAX spider out, because this one, we know it won't actually help at all,
and it'll just speed things up. So we can actually, even though once we've created a plan,
we can add more jobs, we can remove them, we can move them up and down. So you can actually choose,
say you want both the spider and the AJAX spider, you can choose which order they run in,
which you can't do from the package scans. So that is creating my plan, and if I run that,
we can then see the progress
down here, we can see that the spider has run, the passive scan has run,
and there we go. There's the report.
Your report.
That ran very quickly, and it will not have actually spidered the whole of my Tomcat documents,
because you've got a lot more flexibility. So you can actually say where it's going to include.
So you can actually choose URLs as well.
So each of these jobs has its own set of options.
So you can choose whether it's a context, an authenticated user of available.
You could actually choose to crawl just a particular part of your site rather than the whole site.
So there's lots of options here.
So that is how we run it in the desktop.
And that's all well and good, but we want to do these things from the command line.
So what I'll do is I will save and...
Now we're going to have a lovely YAML file ready to go.
Yep.
So I'll call it demo.yaml, and I will close that down.
While you close that down, I think it's important to, again, as a general good practice, right,
to try things out and set them up in the GUI as much as possible.
Test them out if you like.
Always test them out also in a smaller scale, especially if you've got some grandiose website,
and then move into the command line where you have...
have that ability to just prioritize automation and industrialize your actions, if you like.
Exactly.
Yeah, I think that's very important.
And you can then see what's going on much more easily.
We have so many people come into the ZAP User Group saying something's gone wrong in automation
and trying to diagnose it.
I always say, can you use the ZAP desktop first?
Because it's so much easier to see what's going on.
Absolutely.
So here we have our YAML file.
So what...
What we can do now is we can...
I'll end up just going far too far back just to actually...
So I want to do autorun.
And I'll get in the full directory just to make sure it picks up the right one.
..hopefully that's right...
And so, yeah, we've got minus command, minus autorun.
And we're just passing in the YAML file.
So we will then...
And you can hear...
This is all the output you saw in the output tab.
You can see the different jobs running.
And there's the report generated.
So that ran exactly the same as it ran within the GUI.
Mm-hmm.
Now, one thing...
I'll actually note here is we have...
There are some tests here.
So you can see that we actually...
One of these tests failed.
Now, by default, the test gets added at info level, which is why the whole thing didn't fail.
But the automation framework has a lot more flexibility on which jobs to run,
what parameters to pass in, and what to check for.
So you can actually check for a whole load of extra things.
To make sure that the scan is doing what you think it's doing.
And this is something I will cover at a later date in a different ZAP video, I think.
So that is the automation framework.
And last but not least is the ZAP API in Daemon mode.
Okay.
So what I'm going to do now is I want to start ZAP in Daemon mode.
So I'm going to start a new...
Tab and paste in the magic command.
So this one...
Again, I'm starting with the directory.
And I'm putting it in Daemon mode.
But I'm also disabling the API key.
And this is important because when ZAP starts,
it will generate a random API key.
And you can't tell what it is if you start ZAP from the command line.
You can actually specify an API key.
So if you need to use one, that's what you do.
But in this environment, it's a safe environment.
So I'm just going to disable it.
But if you're actually testing websites that are potentially malicious,
you should definitely not disable the API key.
Because there are ways in which we know that websites will try and attack tools like ZAP.
So ZAP is now listening on Localist 9090.
Now, one thing I'll do is I will...
I'll actually point my browser at 9090.
How nice is this?
You've got a pack file you can download, some local links.
You can install a CA, right?
All these things.
And one thing I've got is a link to the local API.
And so this is...
You will see we have components.
So these kind of often match tabs or add-ons.
And each of these will actually have a whole load of what we call views,
which is where you can see things, actions, where you can change things.
And there are sometimes other things as well.
So we'll have a look at core, a load of views, a load of actions.
And at the end, a load of other things.
And other things don't return structured data.
They return something else.
And they actually have shortcuts as well.
So the API is very,
very thorough.
So the API essentially allows you to control ZAP as if you were at the desktop.
And if you remember how many options there were in different tabs,
there's a huge amount of things to do.
And the API is one of the things we added quite early on in ZAP development.
And we found that it was actually too complicated for most people.
So that's one reason why I introduced the package scans and then the automation framework.
So the API is incredibly powerful, but it's also not great for people who are new to ZAP.
And it's not great for a lot of people who want to do standard automation things.
So how do you use the API?
Well, you can actually control the API from this GUI if you want, which is useful for testing.
But it's not so good if you actually really want to automate ZAP.
So we have various API clients, including one written in Python.
And this is kind of the main one.
There's a Python, Java, there's JavaScript, there's a whole range of them.
But the Python one, the one I tend to use most of all.
And you'll see we actually have some examples.
And we have a basic spider scan example.
And this is actually what I've copied.
So let's just...
So you do actually have to install the ZAP Python library.
And then you'll see we've got...
We have the URL, the target URL.
We have the how to actually start ZAP.
But that only works if it's listening on 8080.
So if you're listening on a different port, you've got a different way of doing it.
Then we access the target.
We spider the target and we active scan.
And you'll see we actually have to...
We kick off the spider.
And then we have to loop.
waiting until it finishes.
So things like the spider and the active scan are asynchronous operations as far as the API is concerned.
Something like an active scan could take hours potentially.
So that's why you kick it off.
And then you need to poll to see how far it goes.
So with the API, you can actually kick off multiple spiders, multiple active scans.
At the same time, concurrently.
We don't support that in the automation framework.
And in most cases, I think most people don't need it.
So if you're actually doing large-scale scanning,
I'd recommend kicking off a new ZAP instance for each scan you want to do.
But if you want to do that, then this is an option for you.
And the API is really the only way to go.
And you should really know what your spidering time is if you're doing any sort of CI/CD ahead of time.
Or have at least some sort of SLA defined in terms of why is the spidering taking so long.
That's an indicator.
That something else is going on that is probably not part of ZAPit and the configuration.
But it's something involving the website, the application, the deployment, et cetera.
So it's good to have some sort of indication of what spidering times you're looking at ahead of doing any sort of automation.
Definitely.
Yeah.
If you don't know what you're expecting, then you don't know whether it's working the way you expect it.
We'll never catch on, Simon.
Yeah.
No.
We won't.
So this is I've just copied that file.
And you can see I've got a different target.
And I've actually set I'm using this option to initialize the client because I'm listing on 9090.
So I've actually remember I've got ZAP in daemon mode running on another tab.
And then all I need to do is run this with Python 3.
And again, so we can see we're accessing it, we're spidering it with active scanning and actually gives you some progress here as well.
And I just say, how nice is this, right, that you're able to, you know, for those out there that don't, I've written a ton of Java for open source projects, but for those that, you know, don't like Java, right, you can just do it in Python through the daemon mode, have it listen, and then you just get your results back using the
language that, you know, is your preference.
Exactly.
And in this case, you'll see, we're just dumping the results out in JSON format on the command line.
Obviously, you've got complete choice here.
So this really allows you to do whatever you want to do.
It gives, yeah, the API is the most amount of flexibility possible.
And I think that's the kind of one of the lessons, one of the things that should come out of this is we have a lot of options is
because it's a balance between usability and functionality and flexibility.
And what I'm planning on...
I was just going to say, speaking about options, do you want to quickly hear a story from the trenches on the harshest CI/CD ZAPit rule that I've ever heard of?
Absolutely.
All right.
So we're trying to figure out what's holding back the build.
And we're seeing that it's a security rule that has been triggered.
But it's not one that's been set by any of the security teams, right?
So we're wondering, on the one side, what is this rule?
And on the second side, we're really proud of the fact that we're not writing security rules only within the security team, but also developers and other members of staff have taken that on board.
And it turns out that the entire pipeline has failed because somebody has written the harshest rule in terms of a user agent check for a specific browser version or set of browsers, actually.
And didn't allow or cater for any future versions of, I think it was Safari in that case, where the iOS version number gets passed as part of the update of the actual iOS, you know, when Apple releases an update.
And we had to have a quiet conversation saying, you know, it's great that you're writing your own rules.
But when it comes to rules that fail the whole pipeline, probably a user agent rule slightly
harsh, given that there are no active exploits in history for modern browsers, just based on the version check.
Yes, very nice.
So one thing we're planning on doing is actually writing some more documentation, because we do have this kind of different ways of automating ZAP.
But we don't give you a great deal more help.
So we're going to try and write some more docs.
And it kind of ties in.
We have this getting started guide, and we want to improve this.
So, well, actually, we don't want to change this at all, but we want to have some getting further guides.
And the first getting further guide will be on automation and will hopefully be, we'll start publishing things soon.
If you're watching this several weeks or months after we recorded it, it will hopefully be there.
So just go to the documentation and there may well be then a getting further link underneath here.
But that is...
I think everything I wanted to cover.
I don't know if there's anything else you want to add, Yiannis, about ZAP Automation?
Great.
So, yeah, that was all about introduction to ZAP Automation.
We will be covering the automation framework in another one of these episodes.
But if you have any feedback or you'd like any other, taught us to cover any other topics, then please let us know in the comments below.
Thank you very much.