Hello and welcome to a brand new series of videos about the Zed Attack Proxy, otherwise known as ZAP.
For those of you who don't know, ZAP is a tool for finding vulnerabilities in web applications.
It's open source and completely free.
In this series, we plan on having pretty short videos, 10 to 15 minutes, covering specific ZAP features.
And these could be new features, older features we haven't covered in videos before, or maybe we have covered them, but they've changed quite a bit.
And there are quite a few of those.
So it's probably not ideal for people completely new to ZAP.
So if you are new to ZAP, then have a look at zaproxy.org, because we've got lots of other videos that might be better for you.
But if these videos appeal, then please subscribe.
And if there is anything specific you'd like us to cover, then please mention it in the comments below.
Hope you enjoy them.