Hello, and welcome to another episode of ZAP Chat.
And once again, I am joined by Yiannis.
Hello.
Great. So this week we are going to be talking about the automation framework again.
This is part two of, I actually don't know how many parts it's going to be of.
It's a big framework, right?
It's a big framework.
And I was actually, so what I was thinking of doing,
we would start going into details of the environment and the different types of jobs.
But I mentioned this to Ricardo, that's THC202 online.
He's working, he's one of his key guys working on ZAP.
He's been working with us since 2011.
And he's working full time on ZAP now, thanks to the secure software project.
And I mentioned this to him and he said, great,
I will try and keep creating new jobs so you never get to finish this.
Classic.
I hope he's joking, but maybe not.
He worked quickly.
So, so we're going to see how far we get and exactly what we cover may change over the course of the
period and see what we all get up to on the automation framework, which is definitely one of our
focuses right now.
So without further ado, I will share my screen.
And the first thing I'm going to do actually is take you to,
zaproxy.org, because I just want to show you the documentation here,
which I have shown before.
So documentation, automate, and then automation framework.
And what this does, it shows you, it's all the help pages.
And so you can actually go in and you can see all of the details and you can see, as you see here,
we've got the environment and all of the different options that are
available
in the YAML file.
So what is the environment and how do you use it?
So the environment is kind of the, it's, it is the environment for this particular job.
So it's the context.
I don't want to use the code context.
We use that already in ZAP.
So it is actually a set of contexts potentially, but it is the applications and URLs that we're
dealing with, with this particular plan.
Everything
you're going to be attacking
in the context of your automation set of...Exactly!... actions.
So you want to set this up, this is set up at the beginning.
It has to be the first thing and you can't change it.
So this is for one particular job.
You can obviously change it while you're registering the job, but one in the actual plan, it's fixed.
So the environment consists of one or more contexts.
You have to have a context or the plan won't run, but there's a lot of information here and I'm not going to
go through it
right all of it right now.
We will have another session later on where we're going to more details, but if you have a look, key things are a
mandatory list of top level URLs and everything underneath will be included.
So you have to have at least one URL, and then we have these include and exclude paths.
Now, if you're used to ZAP, then you will know that, well, if you've played around with context, you will know that context is defined by
include and exclude paths, and these are regexes.
So these allow you to find any set of URLs that you want.
And a context can be, typically it'd be an application, but it could be part of an application or it could be an application that spans multiple hosts.
It's really up to you.
So it's... Classic include path typically involves a star followed by, you know, the URL.com domain.
Right.
With a forward slash of whatever is in scope of the penetration test, of course.
And the most standard exclude is anything that is not part of the target host, right?
For a penetration test.
I mean, if you've got, I mean, say you've got example.com, which we'll be attacking, but you'd have example.com, HTTPS, example.com.star, just to include everything underneath there.
And nothing else.
Everything else.
It's treated as being out of scope, but you might well exclude paths.
You might well have your logout URL, particularly if you're doing authentication, or you might have a section of your application that's particularly sensitive that you don't want to touch as part of this particular test.
Yeah, that's a good example, actually.
So those, and I'll show those in a minute, but the rest of this, the authentication part, I said, we will cover that in a future session.
And that's.
So we've got authentication, verification, session management, technology, which, again, we'll talk about probably in the future, and users as well.
So that means there's not so much to cover here, which is great.
The one thing is variables.
So you can have, you can define variables here.
And these then get used throughout the rest of the plan.
And these also cover environmental variables.
So if you've got environmental variables.
Then you can use them in exactly the same way.
Simon, why are environmental variables important in the context of automation?
Well, there's two things.
I mean, one classic one is if you've got authentication and you want to specify credentials and you don't want those hard-coded.
Even on test systems, it's not great to have hard-coded credentials in your configuration.
So you could have these in
you're CI/CD secrets.
And then they will be set in environmental variables and the plan will pick them up from there.
Another one is where you have a generic plan.
So you've got lots of services, half a dozen or dozens of services, and you've got a plan that covers all of them.
So it's you've got set of similar services.
So you want to test in a similar way,
but rather than have a plan for every single service, you have a generic plan
and you use a variable for the URL
and then you can actually set that and run the same plan for all of your services. Yeah very good. And
then we have finally we have these parameters so basically you can choose to fail if there's a
warning if any of the jobs warn or if any of the jobs fail and you can choose whether to write the
job progress to standard out. Very important the fail on error or on warning when you're doing
CI/CD continuous integration or continuous development because that will determine
effectively you know which stage do you get a phone call from the dev team complaining about
the fact that you've just ruined their pipeline. Or if you have scheduled scans and you actually
want to know if something goes horribly wrong. So you might have a scheduled scan and you know
you're expecting some particular vulnerabilities because either they're low priority or I mean
they're false positive
I'll show you how you can set those but it'll show you know you can choose to ignore those
things but you might want to fail if you don't find isn't enough URLs because that might imply
something's gone wrong or if you don't if authentication appears to have failed those
are the kind of things you'll want to fail on. So that was the environment and what I'll do is so
I'm going to now start talking about some jobs and we'll talk we'll you'll see the environment as
as
we're going through this and you can see there's a lot of jobs here, but one is switch to ZAP
and we want to go to the automation tab and if I try and make this bigger sometimes it doesn't
seem to like doing it yep when I'm recording a video but now we can see a bit more of the plan
and I will create a new plan and now you can see the jobs they're not in alphabetical order
they are in kind of a logical order and I think the first few things like alert filter
passiveScan-config, replacer and script they are all kind of configuration type jobs
and so they're the ones we'll focus on and then we've got a set of jobs which are much more
exploring so the requestor, graphql, import, openapi, soap and the two spiders.. Yeah.. then we've got
a couple of delay
jobs delay and a passiveScan-wait so they're another category and we'll cover to
come to those after explaining the exploring side. Then we've got the activeScan the attacking one
all on it's own at the moment and a couple of reporting jobs so they're kind of and I think
we'll go through the jobs in that order really. So.. All right on the top. Yeah so what I'm going to
do is first of all how do you actually create
a context? So you can just say use a default context, but that's kind of empty for me at the
moment and you can configure the context of the environment through the plan, but it's usually
better actually setting it up separately.. So it's much easier just going to go to I'm
going to use BodgeIt it's nice and simple and all I do is just go to the BodgeIt first page and
that will do me.
So we now have BodgeIt in our sites tree and I'm going to right click on the top
URL and including context and I'll create a new context.. so we can..
and what we'll see is we've got an including context we've got the regex and we don't have
any excludes them
the moment and we've got loads of options here for configuring the context. Now not all of
those are supported by the automation framework yet they will be in time, but this is generally
the easiest way to actually use the sites tree and the context dialogue to configure the context
for your automation framework plan and we've got other videos on the context which go into more
detail than context they're a bit older but they're still very relevant.
So now we've actually got our BodgeIt context and we're going to choose it and what I'll do is I'll choose the alertFilter and
the passiveScan and because they're configuration ones they don't do anything so I'm going to choose
a requestor I know it's an exploring one we're just going to use it as a way to actually do
things. So we've now created our context and we can have a look at
this and we can see that by
default we fail on error and not on warning we have no variables and
if we go into BodgeIt we'll see we've got the top level URL and we've got an include regex including
all of that and no exclude regexes. So at the moment they won't do very much none of them
will do anything so what I'll do is go to the requestor
and the requestor's job is to make requests and you can make any number of requests and you don't
have to do at the beginning you can do it at any point. So I will select a URL and we'll select the
top URL and I'll do so that is all this job's going to do so what I'm going to do is actually
start a new ZAP session, a normally ZAP session if you start a new ZAP session it clears everything.
It doesn't clear the
automation framework plan because it's a really useful thing way of being to test things and
you often want to be on to test your plan in isolation and against a clean ZAP session so you
can see it's doing what you expect. Right, right. So that's why we're not clearing the the automation
framework plan. So I will now run the plan and as you see it runs very quickly we're not doing very
much and again we've created this context called BodgeIt and we've made a request.
Now what about these configurations? Well the first one I'm talk about is the passive
scan configuration. So we don't need it - as you'll see we've actually got a whole set of alerts here
and but what happens if you actually don't want the passive scan to work in exactly in
the default way and the default way is to enable everything. So let's pick one particular
alert it doesn't really matter but I'll go for the missing anti-clickjacking header. So say for
some reason you're not interested in this this is not something that you're worried about for
whatever reason maybe you actually need to embed this site in another portal. So what we can do is
we can go to the automation framework plan and configure passiveScan-config. So this is a job
you have to run at the beginning. Well,
you typically have to run at the beginning, because it doesn't have any effect on things
that have already happened it only thing affects things that happen in the future.
So you're configuring a passive scanner and then for whatever it does in the future what's
happened in the past has been and gone. So one thing you can see scan only in scope that's by
default true, enable tags we don't really use tags in automation so at the moment anyway so you
probably don't want these enabled
and you have an option to disable all rules. Now I don't want to do that I just want to disable one rule.
So we can head over to the rules tab.. Yep, yep so we now know that all the rules are enabled
because I'm disabled them and the one I want to is the anti-clickjacking header.
That one there and I want to turn it off which is comes up by default and we can
choose the threshold which is off, low, medium, high. So I will save that
and I've now configured passive scan comfort job how I want you'll notice it's now got a gray
icon rather than the green one because it's changed since we've actually
ran things and I will start the session again and run the plan.
I think what's interesting here is that you can include rules and I think for our viewers you can
include rules which effectively
turn off specific
scans in this case it was one involving the header.. clickjacking, exactly - yeah..
So that took a little bit of you know rewiring in my brain when I first did it because effectively
you know the question is always do you set up a blacklist of rules or a white list of rules
right and generally you want to do what you're doing Simon because if you disable all of them
then you risk disabling something that potentially you want, right? Instead you want to have the scanner
typically configured with a ruleset that is wider than the scope that you have in case throughout
the build process or the test it's a penetration test somebody comes across a specific
misconfiguration of low-hanging fruit or similar which you're meant to catch but you don't catch
because you've started with a disable all rules, right? Exactly, but there again if you've got some
like CI/CD you may well say we've got a set of rules that we absolutely want to run and nothing
else. So we're actually going to fail if we fail to find anti-csrf tokens or missing headers
something like that so as a security professional you might say okay we're going to run a baseline
scan against every PR we know it's going to be quick it won't take long and we're actually only
going to enable a very small set of rules that are absolutely must for us and if they fail we fail
the build or we warn on the build or something like that, but so you've got yeah your two
different cases you know enable and disable
everything and then go and tweak things how you want.
And we'll see we now no longer have the missing anti-clickjacking header.
So that's really what the passiveScan configuration is about it's configuring the
passive scanner and it means you can turn things on and off and whether you can set the threshold
and the threshold is a level at which the rule will actually tell you that something's wrong
and not all of the rules support all
of thresholds but the help should explain when to use which ones and if you have it off then
turn this off then you won't get the any alerts from this particular rule so you know if you're
not interested then turn them off and it will speed things up ever so slightly.
So what else can we do well we've got the alert filter now the alert filter is there if you want
a bit for fine grain control so let's go back
and we've got a cookie without same site attribute and if we have a look at this
we'll see it's jsessionid so you know it's actually a reasonable alert but say this is
not one we're interested in. Say that this this particular cookie that's fine but for other
cookies we might actually want to alert on this so we don't want to disable this rule.
So what can we do with that? So with that what we can actually do is we can
thats what the alert is for and again this is something that has to be you
typically want to do this early on so anything afterwards is affected by the
alert filter. Yeah, yeah that's important right, because you want to basically be
doing configuration first
you know broadly speaking then you want to be doing any sort of discovery or
censorship and then you want to be doing the more active scanning
type of jobs. Exactly. So
all of the things we've
job name you can change this and again we've got this option to delete the global alerts so we have
actually that should be global filters i think that's a mistake there so there's a typo
which i'll need to fix.. so we have filters and we got global filters and we've got context filters
and.. What's the difference between the two? So the global ones apply to absolutely everything
so all of the sites and actually what i'll do is if we go into these ZAP properties
we'll actually see we have global alert filters here and they apply to everything and then we
actually have the alert for context filters in the context themselves itself. Now normally
well i would normally choose the context filters myself because particularly if you're using the
desktop they apply to everything you do
and they don't change when you change a session. Yeah. So keeping things local is you know the
Simon's point of course yeah. Exactly! So what i'm going to do is it cookie without samesite
wasn't it so go up to "Cookie without SameSite Attribute" and i do want this to be a context
specific one and we're going to have it we're going to put it down on false positive
well actually we could put it as info.
Yeah, i think info is better.
One thing is if you have telemetry turned on then we get stats on false positives
and this is really helpful for us because what you're saying is ZAP has got something wrong
and we don't get details so we don't see the requests and responses or anything like that
but we do get stats on the number of false positives per scan rule
and we actually publish these on the website. So if we go back to
the website and go to documentation and statistics then highest false positives last month
and you can actually see "Cookie without SameSite Attribute".
So this is actually one way you know if it's you know this would probably be better to have it as
info rather than false positive. So that's not one where we're going to go okay we're now not
going to we're going to change this rule there's probably no bug in the rule
it's more a configuration thing, but it's you know we do get information about specifically
false positives which is very useful it helps us understand which rules have problems.
So i'm going to say info and i'm actually going to choose the parameters well now it was actually
jsessionid and this means that if another if ZAP finds another cookie
without the samesite attribute which is not called jsessionid then it will raise an alert
for it at low priority rather than info. Now you might say why is that important, right? Well
if all of a sudden a dev team has gone rogue so to speak and decided to just code their own
authentication stack and cookies right this is how you would find that out. Exactly! So let's start
again
and run it and hopefully now we will see ah cookie about samesite attributes so did i get
something wrong? Let's have a look at the yeah filter filter BodgeIt info...
Yes i got three "S" there. Ah, yes! Not the most obvious one so this this is a good reason
always test your configurations before
putting them live because there's you know that's one you could go okay i've now sorted go away
and particularly in this case it was i meant i got an extra thing but it could mean you're
actually your configuration is excluding too much you don't find out things you want to know.
Trying to find this rule on command line right it would just be... Yes.. so let's have a look and yay
this time "Cookie without SameSite attribute" is being logged at information level rather than a
low finding.
So this is something now you can still fail your build or raise warnings or something
if you find "cookies without the SameSite attribute" apart from jsessionid.
Very good! So that is i mean how are we doing how long have you been now?
It's four o'clock so we've been on for 30 minutes minus four six minutes at the beginning
where we chatted about things
minus - yeah i think it's time to wrap up actually.
Okay great well in that case we'll wrap up now and thank you all very much and see you next time.
See you.