Hello and welcome to the first of the ZAP Chat videos and this one is about the authentication
tester. So what is the tester and why would you want to use it? Well if you're just doing manual
testing with ZAP then you probably don't need to bother. You don't need to worry about it because
you can authenticate your target application and you don't have to worry about getting ZAP to handle
authentication for you. So your life is easier. However if you want to automate ZAP then you
probably do need to get ZAP to authenticate your application and that can be tricky and that is why
you might want to use the authentication tester and even though it's a manual tool it's something
that will help with authentication. So for those who don't know ZAP has very powerful authentication
support but it's a little bit complicated.
You have to understand exactly how authentication works for
your application and configures ZAP correctly. This can be tricky and that is why we've added an
option to for ZAP to automatically detect the authentication session handling and verification
that your application needs. So with that I will now share my screen and we'll get stuck in.
So first of all I'm going to show you zaproxy.org
and the reason for doing this is so that I can show you the documentation. So if you go to the
documentation scroll down and you'll see authenticate and the reason for showing you this
is because if it all depends on when you're watching this video. If you're watching this video within a
few weeks of me recording it everything should be as it is now. However we're going to keep on
improving things so if you're watching in a couple of years time some of the
restrictions I mentioned may well no longer be restrictions so do check the documentation.
So now I will switch to ZAP and the first thing I'm going to do is show you context. Now context
are important when it comes to authentication because this is where we configure it.
We do have ZAP has lots of different ways of configuring it including sort of global
configuration via these options here but as soon as you get to application specific configuration
that's where you need a context.
Because this is how ZAP will associate information with parts of your application.
So we just have a look at the default context which you always get then we scroll down we see
authentication and there are a whole set of different options here and you will see the
auto detect option down here and whichever one of these you choose there will be different options
based on what ZAP needs to know. You'll also see a verification strategy.
Now this is how ZAP tells whether you're still logged in. So for traditional web application you
can check every request or response but for a more modern web application you're probably going to
need a poll specific URL. ZAP will also need to know a regex pattern for used for identifying
whether you're logged in or logged out or ideally both. Then we have the users you have to specify
at least one user with their credentials and session management and again there's loads of
different options.
And you'll have to configure different things depending on which of these options you choose.
And ZAP does support script-based session management and script-based authentication so
you can configure ZAP to handle whatever you like. If you can handle authentication then
ZAP will be able to handle it. Obviously if you're using something like two-factor authentication
then you need to be able to get the 2FA token to ZAP but otherwise ZAP should be able to
handle it if you understand how to configure it.
Now you may be wondering why
you don't put ZAP into auto detect mode all of the time because that would make your life easier
and the reason is we know it won't work in all cases. So you know you can either set up your
automation with auto detect and then try and debug it when it goes wrong. If it goes wrong
that can be tricky or we've got this authentication tester dialogue which makes it very easy to work
out whether ZAP can handle it. So I'll cancel that and then you may not be able to see this but
there's a Tools menu at the top and then there's the authentication tester.
Now before I actually run this I need an application to test so I'll cancel that
and go to the Quick Start and I'm going to use an application called OWASP–Juice Shop.
So OWASP–Juice Shop is a deliberately vulnerable application and it's a modern web app so it's a
really good one for us
to test
with. Now what we'll need to do is we will need to set up a user. We'll need to register. So you
go to login, get rid of these annoying dialogues, and I'll use my standard test accounts. Test
at test.com and test123. Actually, now I need to go to not a customer. This is where I register.
We also have to answer a security question with the answer test, of course. So register
there and hopefully now we should be able to log in. So test at test.com and test123.
And you'll see we've logged in because we've now got a basket. So that is all great. Now
what I'm going to do is I'm going to close this browser.
And I'm going to reopen it and I'm going to launch the browser again. Just to point
out that when I launch the browser again, I am not logged in anymore. And now at the
moment, ZAP is not trying to handle authentication. But even if that was handling authentication
by injecting session tokens, then it wouldn't cope with this because in as with many, if not
all, modern web applications, they maintain some authentication state within or session state within the browser
and this is a real pain because if you've got a modern web application and you do automation,
you probably need to explore it using the AJAX spider. That will launch browsers. These
will not be logged in. That is important for a reason I'll explain later.
So now I've done that and shown when I launch the browser, it's not logged in. I'm going
to go to the tools menu and I've got ZAP selected. Go to tools.
And we'll use the authentication tester.
So I've got the login page already in there and the username and password, which is just
test123. Now there's a wait time here. All you need to provide is login URL and credentials.
We have a wait time because some modern web apps take a while to initialize, and we want
them to initialize successfully and to make a whole load of requests, from which we
can detect the session management.
So we have a five-second wait.
If your application takes longer to initialize,
you may well want to increase that.
I'm also using demo mode,
and this just adds in extra sleeps
so it's more obvious what's going on.
I can talk over it.
So I will run the test,
and that will launch Firefox again,
go straight to the login page.
I'll dismiss this manually.
It doesn't matter if I do or not.
You can see ZAP is filling in those fields,
and there we are,
and we can see we've logged in successfully,
and ZAP closes the dialog,
and we can see everything is configured.
So we've detected the username, password,
session handling, and verification URL,
and everything's passed.
So what we'll do now is have a look at ZAP,
and you'll see we have this new authentication test context,
which we can change the name in that dialog.
And if we open this,
and have a look at the authentication,
you'll see that it's set up browser-based authentication.
This is not a surprise because it's the only one that's supported.
We don't use auto-detect
because that would just detect things like form-based authentication
or password or JSON-based.
Because it's a modern web application,
we want to use browser-based authentication
because then we can configure the AJAX spider
to use this when it launches browsers.
And if we scroll down, we'll see it has detected the Who Am I page,
and it has got a regex pattern to identify that we're logged in.
So it has successfully detected everything we wanted to there,
and set users, it will have filled in,
it will add the user that we supplied,
and with session management,
it has correctly identified header-based session management.
It's got the authorization header in twice.
Minor bug there.
Doesn't make any difference.
It still works fine.
But you'll notice we're supplying the bearer,
and then we've got this token here.
And if you look at the help underneath,
you'll see that this is JSON authentication response data.
So when we authenticate the response,
it's JSON, and there's an authentication.token field,
and that's the one we want to use for authorization.
So this means ZAP has successfully detected all of these things.
And what you can now do is if you want to,
you can either use these details as ZAP has configured,
or you can put it into auto-detect mode.
Obviously, the authentication you want to keep as browser-based,
but you can automatically detect the verification or session management,
and everything will work fine.
So everything's good.
So what if something goes wrong?
Well, let's just go back to the dialog so I can just talk through it.
First thing is, well, maybe you can't find a login URL.
Not that you can't find it, but you don't have a fixed one.
We've recently had someone come onto the ZAP user group
and say that their application didn't have a fixed login URL.
It changed every time.
But when the user went to the application,
they'd got redirected automatically.
That's fine.
Just put in the application URL into this field,
and then, or into the configuration for the browser-based authentication.
That will launch a browser.
It'll get redirected.
So that will work fine.
However, if you've got to click on a link or a button,
which then takes you to essentially a random URL,
that will be a problem.
We do have plans to fix that,
but we want to know more real-world examples
to make sure we fix it for everyone.
So if that's the case for your application,
then please get in touch, and we'll ask for more details.
The next thing that can go wrong is the username and password fields,
both of those we may fail to identify.
If that's the case, again, get in touch.
We know that ZAP won't handle everything.
We're aiming to handle the most common cases,
but we want to know the failing cases.
Get in touch.
We'll want to know things like the HTML for those two fields,
and potentially other fields if we're misidentifying one
and using the incorrect field for the username or password.
So we want to know more details about that.
Then another option is that something else can go wrong is session handling.
Perhaps that can't identify the session.
Now, we have this Diagnostics tab,
and this actually has loads of information.
It's a lot of information about the requests and responses.
But what you'll see is we are not recording things
like the host name and port.
So every time we see a new host and port,
we're replacing it with example 0, example 1.
We don't record all of the data.
We just record
the initial headers and structured data.
Now, we keep all of the keys, but all of the tokens
we replace with token 0, token 1.
And if I scroll down here, you'll see hopefully, yeah.
Yeah, here we've got token 439, and we're reusing it.
So we can tell when tokens' values are being reused,
even though we don't know the actual values.
So this is partly anonymized data.
And this should give us enough information
to diagnose what's going wrong with your application.
Do note that, obviously, here we've got OWASP Juice Shop,
so we can tell we're using Juice Shop.
Double check that you don't have any sensitive information
and data in here before sharing this publicly.
But yeah, you can just replace this with something safe,
and then you can share that with us via a new issue
or via the ZAP user group.
And that will hopefully give us enough information to understand
why ZAP hasn't identified the session.
Now, one reason could be that it's a more traditional app,
and you have not made enough requests to actually identify
the session.
And the same thing can happen with the verification as well.
So if ZAP doesn't understand the verification URL,
it could just be that your application hasn't made
enough requests to first identify one.
If that's the case, you can actually launch the browser again,
using this dialog.
And once you're logged in, click on a few things.
That might help.
Otherwise, you may have to identify the verification URL
yourself.
That's not too difficult.
We've got a lot of documentation about this.
So have a look online, but also let
us know what you needed to do so we can see if we can get ZAP
to handle it for you.
So that's it, really.
That is everything that I wanted to share.
And so that is the authentication tested dialog
please try it out and let us
know how you get on, whether it's successful
or whether it fails for you.
And if it fails for you, what the problems were.
Hope you found this video very interesting and useful.
So please leave comments below.
And also get in touch.
Leave comments about other things
you'd like us to cover in this series.
Thank you very much.