Hello and welcome to another Zap Chat video with myself, Simon, and Yanis.
Hello, and we're here to discuss APIs. What are we going to talk about today, Simon?
Yeah. So, confession, we actually failed to record a video last week. So, we're doing two
in one day. We just recorded one on the spiders. And in the previous video, we said we were going
to cover the API jobs, which we didn't. We covered the spider ones. So, now we're going to the API
jobs. So, we're still here on the talk about the automation framework. It's a big framework,
so there's a lot to cover. There'll be more videos after this one. And what we're doing is
we're now on to exploring your application. So, in last video, we explained that exploring is
essential. So, we're now on to exploring your application. So, in last video, we explained
that exploring is essential. Because if you don't explore your application effectively,
Zap won't know about all the endpoints and won't be able to attack them. The spiders are great ways
to explore your applications. But if you've got API definitions, you should absolutely use those
in addition to crawling. Now, if you've only got API definitions, if you're trying to attack
just an API endpoint, then this is all you've got. So, you'll need to import your APIs. But if you're
trying to crawl, you can crawl it probably by one or both of the spiders, but also import the API
definitions before you start to attack. What I like about the API aspect of running jobs is
that you can very easily get the diff of what the API updates have been and then focus on those
updates instead of just having to attack the entire API context that you have, right? If you've got
a swaggered or pasted file, that could run for days. So, I'm really keen to see,
what we're going to be doing here today when it comes to APIs.
Cool. So, let me share my screen and Zap as usual. Now, what I will do is go over to the browser
because the first API definition is this one. So, it's an OpenAPI definition, OpenAPI 3.0,
which is... Now, one thing you'll notice is the URL is swagger.io, and this isn't where PetStore is.
So, that's the first thing. Your API definition may not actually point to the target site. So, that's
something to be aware of.
Make sure you've got that right, right? You don't want to be attacking the wrong API URL.
Exactly. Yeah. And that's key. You know, you always want to know if you're attacking the right thing.
So, let's go to the Automation tab, and I've still got it set up from the spider we did before,
but what we want to do is we will use that, and we use the default context, and then we will...
We've got a set of jobs, and one of them is the OpenAPI one. That's all I will use for the moment.
Now, what I'll do is have a look at the API job. So, we can specify a local file,
or we can specify a URL, which is good, because I'll just paste that one in there.
And then, what I need to do is specify the target, and that is the target. So, it's
petstore.swagger.io slash v2. And there's a v3 as well, which I can show if you think that's useful.
And that should be it. So, I will just run that, and, of course, we'll see what happens.
And, of course, it fails because I forgot to put the URL in the context as well.
URL in the context, yeah.
So, if you modify that, and just...
Save that. Let's try that again. And this time, it's looking better.
So, we can see it's running, and we can see it finished.
So, we can see we actually made that request to the swagger URL.
Go down far enough, we can see the request and response.
And then, we look under the target URL. We will see we're actually making these requests,
and we are getting the responses back. So, this is a...
Using the URL is a really effective way of helping ZAP understand your application properly.
What is it that we are seeing here,
as a set of requests and responses, Simon, that is different to the crawling,
either modern crawling or, you know, traditional crawling?
With crawling, we are exercising the application from the front end.
So, even the standard spider is looking for links. It's looking for forms.
And again, the AJAX spider is filling in forms and doing things like that.
So, it is invoking the application as a user would.
Now, this is really useful and will actually provide us with good context
and potentially some good default values.
But it's quite possible that the API is actually much more thorough
than the front end actually uses.
So there may be extra API points that either the front end doesn't use
or we didn't manage to explore.
So you might have to go through a series of operations on the front end
in order to hit a particular back end API.
And for whatever reason, the spiders weren't able to do that.
If you're going through an application manually, you might be able to do it
because you can have more context and you understand what you're doing.
But the spiders don't really understand applications.
So they might not have explored everything
or it might not be possible to explore everything.
So API definitions are great.
So if you have access to them, then absolutely use them.
And that just shows you how easy it is.
Now, we do have other options as well.
So Zap has very good API support.
And one of them is, another one is Soap.
So a bit more traditional.
And what I'll do is we'll just add a new job.
And while you do that, I think it's important to state
that there is the expectation that you know what type,
and you're going to be able to do that.
So if it's a Swagger.json, we assume that you've either got that
during part of the scoping of whatever penetration test
or exercise you're doing, or if it's a traditional Soap type of job,
then there's a WSDL file or equivalent that you have access to.
There is basically an input required when it comes to APIs
and looking at APIs.
That's very important compared to the traditional crawling
where you're effectively counting on,
you know, the links and the crawling ability
from the front-end perspective.
So don't hesitate to request that during the scoping meetings
that you might have when it comes to pen tests
or rent team engagements.
Absolutely.
And now if the Zap traditional spider actually discovers
one of these endpoints, it will import automatically.
Yes.
What we found is that most applications don't expose
this information.
And in fact, you know, in a pen test,
you might argue that this is actually,
you know, a slight vulnerability because you're giving the attacker
more information than they might otherwise have.
So, you know, we will flag that we found API definitions,
but you might not want those on your public application,
your public endpoint.
So that's why we have these options for importing the APIs
definitions from files and URLs.
One of the cardinal mistakes that I've seen
in the past is that when you're importing a file,
when you're importing a file, when you're importing a pen test
that have gone wrong, is that during scoping,
we have settled on the website being, you know,
website.com or, you know, app.website.com.
And nobody has asked the question,
is there an API.website.com?
And lo and behold, there is, but it's out of scope.
But yet that's the one endpoint backend
that is going to be attacked royally online.
Therefore, you end up with a compromised website
that has had a successful and clean penetration test
because nobody has looked at the API.
The API subdomain of website.com.
So make sure you don't fall into that trap
and use that when it comes to making sure
that you cover that API subdomain.
Absolutely.
And, you know, if you're doing some manual testing,
you could actually, you should be able to identify
some of these things.
So, you know, if you say, okay, this looks like
an open API swagger, something like that,
then ask for that definition.
So let's have a look at, so what I've got,
I've just got a test file on,
because I couldn't find any online ones.
And it shows that we can actually load these things
from file store as well, which might be, you know,
if you haven't got it online, then that's the best option.
Now I don't actually have a service behind this.
So I'm just going to use,
my local Tomcat because it will just 404 all of them,
but it will show you that we can actually,
and I'll remove the open eye, open API.
And if we then, I think the important thing is that
our audience is able to understand how they import
the open API whistle file.
And then you can triage that against the URL that you have
to basically build your own site context equivalent,
but for the APIs,
which then of course is the stepping stone
for further attacks.
Exactly.
And what you'll actually see here is for whistle,
we actually output to the, if you've got the desktop,
so we actually found the service, but we're getting 404s.
But if you have a look at automation,
you see the job actually succeeded.
We've made those requests and you can see they are valid
SOAP requests for the, so, you know,
ZAP has imported definition, actually understands that,
and then has made the correct requests.
Perfect.
Oh, and you seem to have gone fuzzy all of a sudden,
Yanis.
Let me restart my video.
The wonders of a live broadcast, right?
So that's SOAP.
And we do have another option, which is GraphQL.
So let me add the GraphQL job.
And you'll see, this is pretty similar.
So we've got the endpoint,
which again, I will put in as local host.
And this time I've got a simple GraphQL definition
on file store again.
So Simon, what's the difference between a WSDL file
that will get, you know, an OpenAPI definition?
Says the fuzzy meme in the live video
and a GraphQL equivalent file.
They're different definitions, aren't they?
So they're very different technologies, but again,
all they're doing is defining an API.
And these are used to actually typically generate code.
So what people can do is you can have your API definition,
your API definition, and then you can import that
and generate a whole load of code,
which will make it possible for,
and make it much easier for your developers
to develop against.
But it also means we can import them into tools like Zap.
Right, right.
So I've added the GraphQL job
and I will remove the SOAP one.
And again, we will start a new Zap session.
And then if we run that,
we will see, again, Zap ran very quickly
and imported the URLs.
And we will see now,
we've actually got a whole lot of requests,
which are, again, you can see that this time
they look very GraphQL-ish.
And the responses are rubbish ones,
so we could ignore those
because it's not a real endpoint.
We're hitting on a real GraphQL endpoint.
Now, we do,
actually have another,
so Zap recently has Postman support.
And I ought to point out that all of these,
so support for OpenAPI, SOAP, GraphQL, and Postman
were all implemented by students
through Google Summer of Code over different years,
which is actually brilliant.
And this year we had a Google Summer of Code student
working on Postman importing,
and that works from the GUI,
and she's actually submitted a PR,
and she's actually done a PR for support
from the automation framework as well.
So very soon we should have a Postman job
in the automation framework as well.
Great news, great news.
So that is a quick rundown
of how you actually import the API definitions into Zap.
And don't forget that we got loads
of documentation on zeddyproxy.org.
And for the automation framework,
go to Documentation,
automation framework and got links to the videos we've been recording here and here are the full
set of jobs so we've kind of got the environment authentication job tests and then these are all
of the jobs and you can say okay right we'll go in have a look at the GraphQL job and that'll give
you a lot more information including if you want to actually write the YAML directly it'll tell
you give information about all of the the parameters and what they mean so lots more
information there and also check out the blog posts as well so that is the that's the importing
API definitions and we haven't actually discussed what we're going to talk about next but it will be
probably on the automation framework or we might have a slight diversion but there's a lot more to
talk about the automation framework so let me just stop sharing my screen
and yeah you're you're you're fuzzy Yanis I've no idea I know I know from a fuzzy Yanis thank
you all for watching and promise to have unfuzzed myself by the next video yep thank you very much
I haven't decided what we're going to cover next but we aim to do that next week as I said before
please like the videos and subscribe and let us know in the comments what else you know any
feedback and what else you'd like us to cover thank you very much
you