Hello, and welcome to another episode of ZAP Chat. And the observant among you might have realised
that Yannis isn't here, instead of being joined by Antero. So, there's a couple of reasons
for this. One, Yannis has got a new job at the Hellenic National Cyber Security Authority,
which we're delighted for him, which means he's very busy. I'm sure we'll be back before
too long. But I also wanted this opportunity to introduce Antero to everyone. So, Antero,
take it away.
Hi, hi, guys. Thanks. Thanks for getting me here and letting me be part of this project. So,
my name is Antero Silva. I'm a product manager at Checkmarx. And we recently have now the
core team of ZAP onboarded into our world and into our company. And yeah, and I'm glad
to be part of this journey and helping on the ZAP
Open source project in, you know, focusing on the future and, you know, helping out Simon
and the core team on addressing what we should be focusing on first. That's the main current
goal for me within the ZAP project.
Brilliant. I mean, basically, the way we worked out what to work on before was very much kind
of finger in the air, what do we think is most important? And until last year, the only
person I had to worry about was myself, because I'm the only person
I could tell to do anything, because everybody else is a volunteer. Last year,
Ricardo was able to join full time, as many of you will know. So, it ended up myself and
Ricardo going, what do you think we should focus on? So, that's been the process. Now,
we've also got Rick joining as well. And working out what you should do is actually really
hard. Project management is just one of those things that take a lot of time and a lot of
experience. And we've now got Antero to do this, which is great. That saves a lot of
hassle.
But obviously, this is, and Antero has got kind of two views on this, as the same as I have as
well. Because one is we're looking at Checkmarx customers, but two, a very important aspect is
everybody else using ZAP. And, you know, you're not forgotten. And that's a very important part
of this. ZAP is a community project, and we want people to get involved, and we want to do things
that actually you want us to do. So, Antero, can you explain kind of the
new process or the way we'll work?
Exactly. So, I'll start managing the ZAP projects as I'm managing another open source project,
which is KICS for ISE security, which the premises is basically the same. We do have an open source
project, and then we have the enterprise solution within Checkmarx. So, our intention with ZAP,
it's the same. ZAP is an open source project. It's going to be a community project, and we have no
intention of changing that.
In the near or long-term future, there's no intention of changing that. So, the roadmap is basically
constructed upon feedback. That's our main source of knowledge, right? So, I've been in a lot of
customer meetings, a lot of demos, and having your feedback is, you know, it's truly important as a PM
to have access to. So, you can always go into the issues within GitHub for the repository for
ZAP and create a new entry where you can just say, you know, this is the one thing I will have in
mind that will help me a lot in my process. Detail as much as you can in that feature request or in
that new requirement, and we'll, you know, evaluate the possibility of incorporating within ZAP.
Now, look for already existing issues if you want to just, you know, vote for what's already out
there. And based upon that, you know, the number of likes we do have,
in a single feature, we can address if it's more urgent or less urgent to be able to implement it.
So, feedback is key. If you're not, if you don't give us your voice, we won't hear it, basically.
Yeah, exactly. So, hang on, let me just share my screen, and I will now try and
guide you through this.
Yeah, so, so,
basically, this is the ZAP website. So, rebranded as ZAP by Checkmarx. Now, if you go to the
community section, this is where we've got a lot of information here, and one of the key places is
the user group. So, it's a really great place to start, and one reason we often say to do this is
we often get issues raised, or we see people say, you know, I wish ZAP did this. It's like,
it already does. We keep on getting requests for things we already handle, and this could be a
a problem with our documentation you know I completely understand that but ZAP is a big
complex project so it does a lot of things already so if you're unsure about how to do something
the ZAP user group is the place to start but if we say on there great suggestion please raise an
issue or if you want to go straight there then we go down here we will see the the the full set of
repos we've got 47 there but you have a look at the main ones that a proxy and in there we've got
issues now I've actually got quite a few 788 which is yeah it's it's that's been going for quite a
while but what we do is we keep an eye on the things that are the people care about most and
one way you can do that is you actually look at the thumbs up in the first comment and that gives
us the the
the things that people as far as we can see most care about so you can see the top one is actually
persistent fuzzer settings and the next one is macOS distributions not from verified developer
and the first one is from 2015 so but the thing is this is the these are the ones you voted for
the most and what you'll see is we've actually got this new backlog tag and these are as it says
there issues the core team think a higher priority and would like to work on again any given
time so this is what these are the things that we think are important. So when I'm talking to
Antero about okay yeah these are the things we think we should be doing. So if we haven't got you
know obviously we'll have other inputs, but stuff coming from the core team is important, you
know. We know what's going on and we know what things we think we need to do and we know we
have to do. So these are the kind of things we've tagged right now and you'll see the persistent
fuzzer settings and the macOS distribution the two things that we've tagged right now are the
two you've voted for most are in that list. So at this stage there's no promises when we're going
to get any of these things done, because there's a lot of things going on, but we now have more people
than ever to actually work on things. So um so fingers crossed things will actually be able to
do things um much more effectively and much quicker. Yeah, so what I can promise on my end is
that I'm going to review all of these requests
try to assess what's more urgent in my perspective also align with you know the feedback we have been
getting from our Checkmarx customers or even not even customers but potential customers so
what's being requested within the market itself, you know what our competitors have and we don't
things like that and I'll aggregate all of that data and address okay let's focus on what we can
do uh next year. So we are currently constructing the roadmap for 2025
and I'll consider everything so the issues, your direct feedback, our customers feedback all will be
grouped together in one single source of truth and then address, you know with our capabilities
and with our you know resources what we can do and what we'll focus on first. Right so get in touch,
get in touch for the user group vote on issues raise new issues we do want to hear from you you.
You know ZAP is there for people to use
we want it to be as effective as possible so please get in touch. I'll also start a thread
on the ZAP user group for this video and for feedback there. So please comment on that if you
want to, but yeah get in touch and hope to hear from you soon. Likewise see you guys. Thank you very much.