Hello and welcome to another episode of ZAP Chat with myself and Yiannis.
Hello.
So this week, we're not going to talk about ZAP features or not exactly about ZAP features,
rather about how certain ways ZAP features can get created.
In this case, what we're talking about is Google Summer of Code.
So, Simon, what is the Google Summer of Code for somebody who's never heard the term
ever before? What are we talking about?
Yeah. So Google Summer of Code is an initiative from Google, surprisingly enough.
And it's all about getting new people involved in open source. And it's been running for a long
time. I should have checked to see how long it's been going for. But it's a great initiative.
We have taken, the ZAP team has taken part in it for many years. And we've had some
absolutely key features implemented through this program. So it's been really big for us.
And we count Google as a sponsor of ZAP just on this basis because it's given us so much benefit.
So that is what Google Summer of Code is.
Sorry, does it take place during the summer?
Yeah. So it used to be just students, but Google have expanded it now. So I think anyone can take
part.
And what happens is organizations apply to Google and they say they want to take part
and they've accepted. Then potential contributors can propose projects or pick projects that are
proposed by the open source projects. And then Google will assign a certain number of projects
to each organization. There's then a bit of a bun fight with an organization to see which
projects get selected. And then Google will pay
those contributors to work on the projects over the summer.
And the projects can be of different lengths. This kind
of changed recently, but all the details are on the Google Summer of Code site,
and I'll share a link with that later and put it in the YouTube chat as well.
So overall, we've got an initiative by Google to help open source projects. I remember
GSoC back in 2007 when OWASP was flirting with it and it was, you know, it was a,
question which projects are going to be part of the Google Summer of Code as you say a little bit
of a bum fight like you know who gets the the resources and what what kind of features
has the Google Summer of Code delivered for ZAP? So some of the absolute key ones what i'll do
just just while we're mentioning you know here's my t-shirt so so what's happened is ZAP has
taken part in Google Summer of Code for quite a few years as part of the OWASP organization.
Obviously, ZAP is no longer part of OWASP we're part of the software security project which is
part of the linux foundation so we've talked to the linux foundation Google Summer of Code admins
and they've said we can take part. So we're really hoping to take part this year again
and if for any reason say linux foundation doesn't get places or there aren't enough places for ZAP
then we will do our best to make sure
this happens one way or another. There's a set of companies who are using ZAP
and have said they'll sponsor things like this so we want to take part in Google Summer of Code
and we want to sponsor students one way or another so.. yeah this is something which we are
going to make happen. We're going to continue, yeah absolutely. So let me just share my screen
and.. We've got lovely documentation going back to 2012.
Yeah, so if you what i was going to do actually is go to just show how i get here so from
zaproxy.org if you go to community and then scroll down through about ZAP get in touch report
problems and get involved you'll see you've got the contributing guide which is very key
and lower down here there's a new set of pages we only added recently for Google Summer of Code.
And what
this page, this landing page has some advice and guidance which we'll talk about in a bit
then it goes back and yeah these are all the years that ZAP has taken part
and the first five we've got separate pages for we will add pages for the others it just takes time
and we just we just wanted to get this pair of this set of pages live as soon as we could.
So if you go back to.. right back to 2012 then the first year we took part was actually
three projects which wasn't i i think the first time you take part a project you only have one
Google Summer of Code projects, but we ended up with three which is a bit bizarre, but that
was actually two of these were through a OWASP. So the.. the crawler was a redesign with session
support that's the traditional spider and that was the only project assigned to ZAP, but then the
Ajax spider was actually
designed to another OWASP project but it turned out that was a very small shim around another
project which wasn't OWASP project so in the end it got transferred to ZAP, because that was
the Ajax spider and it was a wrapper around crawljax. So the Ajax spider came out of Google Summer
of Code and as did a lot of changes to the traditional spider and web socket testing
which was actually assigned to mozilla, but then i i joined mozilla and
this was it was it was always designed to intended to be ZAP project anyway it was just
sponsored by mozilla. So we end up mentoring them as well. So very first year Google Summer of
Code we mentored three projects which was challenging, but really good. Then 2013
BIRT reporting which hasn't actually that hasn't survived, but there's a lot of zest enhancements
a load of Session Handling and SAML v2 support.
Then 2014 advanced fuzzing, SOAP support, Access Control Testing, 2016 bug tracker support and
we hope to be adding to that more in fairly soon. 2018 the Authentication Helper and scanning web
sockets the first phase, 2019 second phase of scanning web sockets, 2020 GraphQL support another
big one, 2021 out-of-band Application Security Testing
another really big change and Retesting Alerts. Then 2022 Param Digger this is actually a a port of a burp suite add-on which is
add-on.. yeah.. very useful and then 2023 the Browser Recorder and Postman Support. So as you can see
some really significant key developments have been implemented by students working on Google
Summer of Code. Students and beyond, yeah absolutely
and 2024 is a year that we're planning right now. So.. Exactly!.. i can see the page start getting involved.
So what are we doing this year when it comes to the GSoC? So, as always what we do is we suggest
a set of projects, but we have no problem if people come up with their own ideas.
If you come up with your own ideas it's always good to chat to the to us the ZAP core team
we'll get into discussion about it. We always get some proposals that are a bit
left field and haven't been discussed with us and we're going to reject those. I'm sorry,
but if it's completely new and we know nothing about it, you haven't talked to us about it,
it's going to go unless it's really interesting, but it's it's too by the time we the
the the call for papers or whatever you want to call it has finished by the time the proposals
are in we have to base we have to decide on that basis. If it's completely new to us it's
going to be somewhat out there and we need to we should have discussed it by then. So get in touch
that's the main thing... and and you are competing for those of you out there thinking you know i
want to do my own. You are competing with some brilliant ideas that have come up
through community so and we'll go through those for example AI and how that can be
used in the context of dast dynamic testing, that's one example. We talked about a number of times
how our GUI perhaps needs a revamp.
Well, the topic has come up of,
well, do we need a web-based GUI as well?
And do we need to augment the existing GUI
instead of just updating it with another web-based UI?
And of course, gRPC support,
which is, I mean, it's going to be needed
it's, you know, a new protocol.
That is something that, you know, is just going to be a feature
that's going to be added over time.
So there you go.
You have three things already,
and we'll talk about these in more detail.
But please remember, you know,
one week before the deadline,
submitting your own new cool idea
without engaging the community
really is not going to drive a GSoC project, right?
It's about being part of that initiative.
Yeah.
You know, we've had some great proposals.
So one of the ones which was a,
sounded like a left-field proposal,
was actually a suggestion to create a Chrome add-on
to add what was effectively a heads-up display.
Now, this was suggested by a student called David Scrobonia,
and we got in touch with him and said,
look, this is unexpected,
partly because we've actually got a proposal for HUD already,
but it's internal.
So we were already planning to create the HUD,
but we decided we didn't want to use a browser add-on
because we thought it would be easier.
Well, we thought it'd be more flexible
if ZAP injected the content,
rather than having an add-on,
whether it's a good idea or not, it's another matter.
So we talked to David and he agreed
that he would actually work on the proposal
that we were thinking of.
We had a POC working,
but we had nothing actually published.
And we agreed that it'd be best
if he didn't take part in Google Summer of Code
because it was a huge project
and we knew it wouldn't get completed in one summer.
So he was actually fine
with that and he worked on it
and he carried on working on it
and it got published a couple of years later or something.
But so we worked with him and it was a great idea
and it wasn't one of the projects we proposed.
So we're very happy to hear about new suggestions,
but just get in touch and talk to us.
So Simon, you mentioned that this particular feature
took a little while to implement.
What sort of timelines are we putting around, you know,
small, medium, and large Google Summer of Code projects?
So there are guidelines on the Google project.
I can't remember what they are,
but there's a certain number of hours.
And so we'll have to have a look into that,
but have a look at the Google website,
Google Summer of Code.
And so I think if we go back, then that is the link.
Yep.
So this is, so basically the Org applications
are open now and it's got details there,
but basically we're kind of looking
at the getting the organization.
So the organizations can apply.
So OWASP and the Linux Foundation
will be applying right now.
So we will, obviously once we know that the organization,
the Linux Foundation has been accepted,
then we can update, we can double check
on how long the projects are,
but basically they're kind of over the summer.
So they are medium sized projects,
but there are different options,
but the ones that we've got are fairly significant.
And so, you know, gRPC support.
So that is a new protocol
and we know that, you know,
ZAP will intercept these requests,
but we will show them as binary requests,
and this is not unusual.
So any new protocol comes along if it's using it,
it is based on top of Web Technology.
We should be able to see them, but we don't actually, ZAP doesn't understand them and can't present them to the user in a useful way and can't do fun things like attack them.
So this is a really good project if you're interested in protocols
and this is one where ZAP is written in Java.
So good Java skills are pretty essential for this.
And I remember, you know, talking about binary protocols.
I remember, you know, when everybody was using parts of Adobe Flash or other technology for binary, and it was all about supporting RTMPS or some other similar protocols.
So gRPC falls in that category of a remote procedure call protocol
and it's just part of expanding the protocol interface to be able to see more than just a binary blob in your view.
So that's going to be an amazing feature.
Also.
potentially, we could see, you know, depending on how Google Summer of Code goes, whether or not specific payloads could be injected as part of the parameters inside those gRPC calls.
But first, you've got to read the protocol, right?
First, you've got to be able to sit in the middle of it.
And this is, yeah, this is very, you know, you start with a new protocol, basically, you have to, you know, code ZAP to understand the protocol and display it to the user so that, I mean, you just get good feedback that way
you go, okay.
Yep, this is looking right.
But then if you do that, then it's quite easy to get ZAP to understand, this is what you can attack
and we have these layers of separation.
And one of the things we have is input vectors.
An input vectors are the things that ZAP can attack.
So as long as, if you add input vectors for a new protocol, then all of a sudden ZAP can attack them.
And we don't have to make any changes to any of these existing scan rules.
So you've got existing rules.
Existing scan rules that say to SQL injection.
If ZAP understands the gRPC protocol, then the SQL injection rules will work.
And then, you know, if we get things like SQL errors coming back in the responses or we get long delays when we inject timing attacks, then we will be able to find vulnerabilities with no extra changes using existing rules.
Having said that, there may well be new rules that are specific to gRPC.
Yeah, absolutely.
Might be the new set of payloads, right?
I don't know what SQL injection is for the gRPC.
So for something like SOAP, ZAP understands SOAP, and this was a Google Summer of Code project.
And part of that was actually adding some SOAP-specific scan rules.
So this, again, this is understanding the protocol, teaching ZAP what can be attacked.
And then potentially adding new payloads and new attacks, new active scan rules for targeting gRPC.
Good old fuzzing.
The next one is not a fuzzing or a protocol feature, but it talks about the web-based UI.
So what's this about?
Yeah.
So as you know, Yiannis, we've got various surveys.
We've had them over the years.
It's a good way for us to get feedback.
And we do get some feedback online and via user group and things like that.
And one thing we do keep on hearing is that the ZAP desktop UI is not as modern as it could be.
It is somewhat old-fashioned,
it's a bit clunky,
it's a swing-based GUI.
So, yeah, we know it's a bit old
and we know that some people don't like it.
Now, some people do like it
and what we've been talking about within the team is,
what do we do?
One option is to revamp the swing-based UI.
And we could completely change how it works, its look and feel,
but then there's a danger of actually pissing off the people who do actually like it
and have got used to how it works.
So one suggestion that came up was, well, why don't we actually have a web-based GUI?
And this is not that unusual for desktop applications these days.
Quite a few are going down this route.
Now,
some of them are using Electron as a kind of basis for that.
But that's not the direction we want to go,
because ZAP already has a runtime and you already need to use the browser.
So let's just use the browser.
And so what we're talking about is a web-based GUI that drives the existing ZAP API.
ZAP has a very thorough API
and if you start working on this and you find out that there are
API calls that you need that aren't there,
then that's something we can add in the core team.
So this is an unusual project in that. It's not one that requires Java skills.
It actually requires sort of modern web app skills.
So we're talking about JavaScript and preferably TypeScript.
There's a lot of things that you get for free in the modern browser,
like, you know, the memory management.
Imagine having a sites tree, you know, a big spidering operation that you've run.
And, you know, for all the memory that Java can consume,
if you do that lookup for a specific URL or, you know, a specific parameter,
it's much easier to do that in the browser because browsers are now built in a way
that they can handle, you know, big chunks of memory being addressed for searching, right?
Swing, for all its downsides, is the default still Java,
but the interface Eclipse still uses as one example.
And there isn't a better one for the lack of what we have out there.
It's not that Oracle or SANA, you know, whoever out there has put out,
or, you know, the Apache Foundation has put out a different set of libraries that we can use.
So I think your, you know, your description of having a web-based GUI
to augment the existing GUI goes a long way as to what the future should look like.
Also, there's probably features that should not be,
in the web-based GUI, like, you know, I can't think of how you would do,
shall we pick, like, you know, an advanced fuzzing session, for example, right?
Maybe, I mean, this is one where I think it's an opportunity to completely reimagine the ZAP interface.
And, you know, we had a go at this with the HUD and I still like the HUD,
but I think this, and maybe this web-based UI,
could interact with the HUD in some way, but I think that it's separate.
So it is a UI focused on ZAP.
So we're not having that overlay over the target application,
but you don't have to copy the existing ZAP GUI.
And in fact, you probably shouldn't.
So it's an option to think of it in a different way and hopefully more flexible way.
So maybe something that, you know, different types of users can configure in different ways
so they can handle it.
And then get ZAP to work the way they want it to work.
Yeah. And it goes back to the user persona side of it.
Absolutely.
So you have, in essence, you've got a couple of personas that are meant, you know, for the web-based UI.
Anything that's CI/CD, operational, DevSecOps, people are used to in operation rooms, right?
Not just SOCs, just operation rooms.
Having a web-based browser open and seeing specific things happen in real time.
I think that's a place where, you know, the web-based UI could excel.
Make some scanning as well.
I just don't see the web-based UI being there, you know, for the red teams out there or the, well, I don't know.
Maybe it is out there and I'm, you know, I'm, you know, in like that button that you click in order to be able to do a specific feature.
But there's definitely stuff to be looked at in terms of which personas would best fit the web-based UI and which, you know, are better in that swing world of the GUI.
Yeah.
I think this is something where, you know, we definitely don't expect the full functionality of the ZAP desktop to be reply by to be implemented as part of this project.
It's very much a starting point.
And it's something that, you know, let's get something, the key features within ZAP working in a web-based UI.
And we share it with the community and get feedback and see, you know, who likes this?
You know, does it work for people?
What types of ZAP users actually like, you know, want this?
And how do they want to use it?
So it's one where this is almost like a proof of concept, but a working one, a non-trivial one.
And it's something we can release and for people to play around with.
And then this is something that can then be developed over the years.
You know, this is something, if we get the direction right, then this could be a major
part of ZAP going forward.
Absolutely.
And speaking about direction and an open-ended GSoC so
last but not least, right?
Especially in the current hype that is out there,
AI integration.
Yeah.
This is one which is, yeah, very speculative because, you know, AI is obviously a big thing
right now.
And people, you know, we've had quite a few people get in touch and say, does ZAP support
AI integration?
And our answer is, well, what do you mean by that?
Because there's lots of potential things.
And I think the key thing is...
You asked that question to society, right?
Does, you know, does anything support AI integration?
And one thing you have to think very pragmatically about this, because, you know,
how could AI help ZAP and where wouldn't it be so relevant?
For example, somebody suggested, well, AI could generate payloads.
We can't do that on the fly because, you know, if we have these input vectors, which I'm
mentioning before, and we have scripts, which can generate input vectors.
So you could say, well, we'll get this script to call AI.
Well, input vector scripts or input vectors get called thousands of times a second, a
ridiculous amount.
Performance-wise, you can't make a remote call to an online AI to ask it what the next
payload should be.
So, you know, if you're talking about, well, let's get AI to analyze every request
and response that ZAP sends, no chance.
You'll absolutely kill the performance.
So you have to kind of think very carefully about where it's practical to integrate AI.
And that's the important thing.
And this is one where we've got some ideas, but we're really interested in what other
people come up with
and if you're listening to this and you're not interested in taking part in Google Summer
of Code, but you've got suggestions on how AI could be integrated, then get in touch.
You know, please let us know,
but this is something that is, you know, if you've got a lot of imagination, you've
got ideas around what AI can do, then this is a great project for you.
Absolutely.
If you look at AI also, integration, you know, that's a broad term.
Intentionally, right?
We didn't put ML.
We didn't go very specific.
We didn't say payloads to allow that open-ended discussion to take place.
Yeah, I think that's really important.
Finally, Simon, when it comes to having my own idea about a project.
How do I get in touch?
So we have, there's loads of ways to get in touch.
If we go back up here and then go to community, there's a section called getting touch.
So we've got the user group.
Actually, the developer group is probably best if you've got an idea you're thinking
of implementing
or the HUD group for now.
IRC.
We're on IRC,
European office hours best.
So I'd say the developer group or IRC are probably best.
But I'm on Twitter.
So ping me.
We're also, we're still hanging out in our Slack in the Project ZAP channel.
But we should be easy to find.
If not, you're really not trying hard enough.
Excellent.
So please, people, get in touch.
Give your input when it comes to the GSoC for 2024.
And more importantly, also, be part of this journey, right?
So whatever projects are going to be selected, you're going to be able to see the progress.
See what people are doing
and probably see the actual output in the lovely GUI of ZAP, which we're about to replace.
But definitely we're thinking about augmenting.
Yeah.
So just going to where is stop share.
Yeah, that's better.
Yeah.
Google Summer of Code is a great initiative.
We've had huge benefit from it in the past.
And really looking forward to this year's projects.
And one thing, quite a few, several Google Summer of Code participants have ended up in the ZAP core team.
It's a really great way to get deeply involved in the project.
Just doing GSoC won't get you on the core team because you're kind of paid to do that.
So we need to see you carry on after that.
But if you carry on contributing to ZAP, then you can definitely get on the core team.
And once you get on the core team, you'll get job offers.
Everybody who's ever been on the ZAP core team has had job offers.
And some of us have even accepted them.
So there you go.
That's a bit of the future.
Starts with a simple Summer of Code project and you end up coding ZAP and being paid for it.
What more do you want as a career progression in 2024?
Exactly.
So thank you very much for listening.
We have a running joke about saying exactly, by the way, which I've been saying too often.
Exactly.
Thanks, everyone.
Thanks a lot.
Bye.