Hello and welcome to another episode of ZAP Chat with myself and Yiannis.
Hello. Quite an exciting day today. We have authentication in the works. Simon,
what are we discussing today? Well, we're going back to the
automation framework. We've done several videos already on the automation framework. Authentication
and automation, you get those mixed up easily. Well, I do anyway. So, automation framework,
but authentication in the automation framework. And this is something that quite a few people
asked about. And so, yeah, that's what we're going to cover this time. We may well have other
episodes on authentication. We're not going to cover everything, but we're going to try and cover
the easier case to start with. So, that's what we're going to do. I'm going to also propose a
future video that talks
about authorization to just make sure that you've got the three A's to grapple with in future
videos. So, we've got Juice Shop as a test site, I believe. Is that right?
Yep. OWASP Juice Shop, a deliberately vulnerable modern web app, which is a very
useful one to play around with. So, one thing I want to talk about first is with authentication.
So, what we're talking about here is very much around the automation side, because if
you're doing a manual pentest, you can authenticate. If you've got credentials,
you can authenticate yourself, you can manage the sessions. You don't have to worry about
ZAP handling the application sessions for you. If you're doing automation, it becomes much more
difficult because you're not there to log in. So, what we need to do is get ZAP to handle. Well,
you can handle authentication or ZAP can handle it, but we're really talking about ZAP handling
authentication. Now, ZAP can
handle pretty much anything, but it might be painful. We've got lots of options, and in many
cases, you have to really understand how everything works in order to configure ZAP.
And we've had cases where I know of at least one very large bank in the U.S. that tried to get
authentication working with one of their apps, and they couldn't do it with any of the commercial
scanners. They could only do it with ZAP because ZAP is so configurable, but they knew what they
were doing and they knew
exactly how things worked. So what we now recommend, even though ZAP supports loads of
different types of authentication, we really recommend you only use one, which is browser-based
authentication for web UIs. If you've got an API with no UI, then it's no good because you need a
browser. But we recommend the browser-based because you don't have to understand as much
in most cases. And if it's a modern web app, you need to use the AJAX Spider to explore it.
And it is a real pain actually injecting user sessions into a browser. It's very much
application-specific. I've managed it in some apps, and some apps have just failed completely.
So if you use browser-based authentication, then we can use that in the AJAX Spider.
We can launch the AJAX Spider, we'll launch browsers, we use browser-based authentication,
log itself in, and then carry on exploring the app. And you need that session state in the
browser for the AJAX Spider to work properly. So browser-based is the way to go for everything
apart from APIs with no UI. It makes sense, Simon, because if you look at big websites,
one of the basic layers of obfuscation, because it's not really a security control,
they have is that aspect of requiring browser interaction to stop the basic script kiddie
brute force attacks and the form field of username, password, every second factor, whatever else
is there. And we used to solve this problem by introducing CSRF tokens, whereby you had a
request and a response, and therefore you had to potentially use Selenium or something else to go
get the tokens, submit it back, and all that lovely stuff.
So what you're seeing is modifications of that in modern applications. Why? Because they're not
necessarily trying to make the lives of their pentest teams more difficult, but what they are
trying to do is stop the requests and responses on the basic script kiddie attacks of somebody
wanting to find an account of admin admin on the website, which of course doesn't exist.
So I think browser-based is going to be the way forward for a number of things because more and
more people are relying on the verification of the human element,
through that browser-based interaction.
That's right. And in some cases, it's just a side effect of modern web apps.
You know, we can, modern web apps have so much going on in the browser, and that state of the
user being logged in has to be there in the browser. So if the browser doesn't understand,
doesn't have the data to know that it's logged in, then it can't add the relevant headers via
JavaScript.
You know, it doesn't,
it doesn't get the right responses back from the server, so it can't access all the data it needs
to. It doesn't matter if ZAP is injecting things after the browser sees it, the browser doesn't
know to actually make the relevant requests so it can get the data back that it needs.
Yeah, absolutely. And we're going to see more and more of that. So talking about automation
in authentication, right, is going to be exciting. Let's have a look.
Okay. So let me share my screen.
And we have ZAP. So what I'm going to do is just start with, let's have a look at Juice Shop.
So, so I've got it running. I'm running it in a Docker container because that makes it nice and
easy. And I've not, you know, so it's, I've not made any changes to Juice Shop. It's just out of
the box. So to speak, and I am now going to launch my browser Firefox, of course.
And we will.
So is the browser configurable if I didn't want to use Firefox and I wanted to use
chromium or Chrome or Edge.
So if we have a look, you'll see, we have pull downs. So we've got Chrome, Firefox,
and Safari. I'll have to see whether Safari is a pain. I mean, it is Chrome. Chrome and Firefox
are the, the, the two browsers. We are the primary ones we support.
So, you know, we support it comes down to what selenium supports
as well. So because we're using selenium is it selenium or selinium? I never know.
Not sure let's go with the, the, the double E selenium. Right? Sounds more,
more Greek to the word selenium is the ancient word for the moon that we have.
Oh very good. We learn a new thing every day. So this is Juice Shop and we will see, go to the
account and we can log in.
Now, I've only just started Juice Shop, so I don't have an account.
But we can, as not used to customer, so I'll do my usual ones of test@test.com and test123.
I have to repeat the password, test123.
We need to look up who owns test.com, the domain, because the numbers are just going to be smashed with requests.
It should be example.com, really, it shouldn't have been in mine.
Elvis' sibling's middle name is not surprisingly test.
So I will register that, and we now have the login page, and you'll see that is 3000/#/login.
I'll copy that just in case, and we will then go test@test.com and test123, and we will log in.
And we've logged in.
Great.
So we'll see the account there, test@test.com, everything's wonderful.
So that was nice and easy.
We have registered an account, and if we actually have a look at the alerts, let's see.
I think we should see, if we scroll down, we'll see that it's a modern web app.
We've recognized an authentication request, and we've recognized session management response.
So we found the authentication token.
So this gives you an idea that ZAP has some understanding about what's going on.
Now, like I said, there's lots of options for authentication, but what I really recommend,
and it's much easier to use a desktop rather than doing everything in automation,
because you can see what's going on.
And one of the tools we have in the desktop, which I think we've covered before,
is the authentication tester.
And you can see I was testing.
So we've got the Juice Shop login there.
Remember, it's the last one
test@test.com, test123, and I'm going to use Firefox.
Wait five seconds.
And we will just check to see whether this works.
And you'll see when this launches.
Sorry.
Yeah.
So we'll see, actually, we were not logged in there.
It's gone to the login page.
And the five-second thing is because we found that quite a few modern web apps
actually take quite a long time to initialize.
So I've seen 20 seconds, which is horrific.
And, you know, not a good user experience,
but we have to deal with things as we find, not as we'd like them to be.
So, you know, and what happens,
we actually get a page-loaded event from the browser really early on.
And then
it sits there for two, three, five, 10, 20 seconds while it's loading
everything in the background.
And we want to make sure that the page is actually fully loaded.
So it starts making requests to the server.
So ZAP sees them.
So ZAP can identify a good verification URL.
Right.
So it might even be longer than five.
It could go up to 20.
Yeah.
And that's why we, we kind of, that's why we default to browser to
Firefox rather than Firefox headless.
And that means you can see.
What's going on.
You can go, nothing's happened yet.
I'd better increase the timeout.
Right.
So what's the demo mode option?
Demo mode is for me.
So this is actually for when I'm on stage at a conference, because this
goes through too quickly, it will launch the browser, fill things in, and
you can't see what's going on.
So I think it's like a two second delay between typing something in the
password field, typing or the user field typing something in the
password field, clicking on things, and this will actually cope with username
and password on different pages, so to speak.
So it kind of helps, it allows me to, to talk through things on stage or in videos.
So you don't need to use demo mode, but the key thing here is everything's
passed, which is good.
This is what we want.
And this makes our life easier.
Now, if it does, if things don't pass, then it's not the end of the world and
that's something we'll probably cover in a future episode.
Debugging authentication prior to any automation, which you need to do because
otherwise the plan's just going to fail.
Right?
Correct.
So what happened is we created, or the tester created this authentication
test context, and what you'll see is under authentication, and I'll make
this a little bit bigger so we can see it, it's chosen browser-based now we do
have the option for auto detection.
That's not, it, having everything down as auto detect doesn't really work.
The best option is to choose browser-based and then you'll see we've, it actually
has, what ZAP will have done, it would have actually set this to auto detect.
And then when it, it, the auto detect worked and it then went, okay, we found
this URL, which is who am I, so that's the URL that we can actually hold to see
whether we're logged in.. Right!..
..and then, and what we're doing is we're checking for a regex pattern,
which includes the, the username.
The username.
Right.
And the pull through verification is a page that you normally would get a 404,
unless you had the authentication tokens or, you know, a 302 or, you know, whatever.
Something now in this case, I don't think, I think it comes back as a 200 anyway,
which is a pain, but we've identified a pattern, which is unique and ZAP will have
tried this both with the, the session tokens without them.
So we're pretty confident.
This is a good page and we can tell the difference.
Yeah.
ZAP has also created a test user and it is also, if we look in session
management, it's created header based session management, it's added the headers
twice, that doesn't matter, minor bug, fix that at some point, but everything is good.
So what we can do now is we can use this.
We can actually use this context in an automation plan.
Now, what I'll do first is actually, I will create an automation plan and I will
use the default context just to be a contrary and we'll, you have to select a job.
I'm going to select the request to job.
And what I'll do then is go into this context and we can set parameters variables,
but then we edit the context.
You'll see.
We could got the
include regex, the exclude regex and the technology, but we can't edit the authentication.
Sorry about this.
We plan to add this.
We will add this, but these things take time.
We've got a lot going on.
So you can't edit the authentication.
This means I cannot add authentication to this context.
Does this mean the authentication plan, the authentication framework doesn't support authentication?
No, the automation framework does support authentication.
We just don't allow you to edit.
So what can you do?
Well, what we need to do is we need to actually scrap that plan and use the authentication test because
this is the one we have set up authentication on and I'll go for the requester again.
And the reason I'm doing this is, what I want to do is actually make a request and we'll
see, here's a telltale sign that we have got authentication set up
because we've got a user we can choose
and I'm going to make a request..
I actually like the fact that the authentication test is immutable in the
context of the plan, because if you look at, you know, just the sequence of events, let's say from
a red team perspective, right, you want to have figured out absolutely everything around how
authentication works before you go into, before you go near, you know, anything relating to
automation, right? And that's a general principle not related to just security. It's, you know, you
don't automate something unless you've got the absolute swim lane sussed out in terms of what
are the precise steps that need to be followed. So I don't see it as a bad thing to be editing,
you know, the authentication. Now, it could be like when you have nuances and so on, it could
be a little bit more difficult because you've got to create a new context and to do that, you've got
to run the browser-based, you know, authentication. Not necessarily. Let's see, because what
I've done, so I've, using this authentication test context, I've added a request, which, so this
one was, we use it authenticated. So we've said the user, if you don't say which user, then it'll
be unauthenticated request. We're very explicit about, you know, we do what we're told, or ZAP
does what it's told, and we're requesting this page. Now, I will start a new ZAP session. I think
we mentioned this before, a new ZAP session will wipe
everything apart from the automation plan, because it's really useful to keep that there.
And I will now run the automation plan. And we should see the browser launching and
logged in. There we go. Should, and after five seconds, it will stop. And it says everything is
okay. But if you work in security, you know, you never believe everything that's just shown to you
like this. So let's have a look at the history. And we will see down here, there are actually
two requests for the whoami page. The first one is auth. The source is auth. So this is the
authenticator. And this is, so this has made the request, and you'll see the authorization token
there. And the response all looks good. We've got the email in there, last login IP, etc. and then
this is the manual one. This is the one I added
via the plan and you can see, again, it's got the bearer, but it's got very little else. So the other one came
from the browser. This one's just come from the automation framework. And again, the response is
good. So that's it. Everyone's happy. It's all sorted. We can now go and add extra things. So
you can then do things like the AJAX spider, active scan, all those things. A quick tip on that.
You could always check the size, right, in terms of the URL that you're verifying, that you use to
verify. The size of the length of what comes back typically changes if you're successful or
unsuccessful.
Well, let's just show that as you've suggested. So right-click, right-click anywhere on ZAP to get
loads of options. And we're going to open in the request editor. So here's our request. And I'm
going to take out
the cookie and authorization header. And then just send that. And you'll see here, the response is
just user. And we get 200. And of course, we can then see back down here, I have made ZAP the text
bigger, which is why it's all scrunched up here, just so it's easier to read on the video. We can
see 125 bytes when it worked, and then 11 bytes
when it failed. So we can see from the size, even though we're getting a 200 response code back
in each case.
So you've set this up, but it's not quite what you want. You want to tweak things. So let's have a
look at this authentication test context again. Now, as said, it's set up browsed-based
authentication. Now, we could... Obviously, it's got this... It's sending pull URL. This is
fine. We can leave it like that. But what we can do is we can also change it back to auto-detect.
So this means that if something changes in your application, maybe we've chosen a URL that
is currently there right now, but in the future, that API call gets changed,
then your plan would fail because we're pinging an API that no longer exists, is no longer supported,
and then everything fails.
So if you change it back to auto-detect, then ZAP will auto-detect the right URL to verify every
time. And the same with session management. We're going to go back and change to auto-detect
session management. And we don't want it to be called authentication test. We'll change it to
Juice Shop. And actually, when we go to authentication, we don't want Firefox popping
up every time when we automate it, so we can change it to Firefox headless.
So we can change this context. That has not changed the context in the automation framework.
If we have a look here, it still says authentication test, because the plan is different from the
context we've created. We created that context. There's now no link between them. And this came
up recently on the user group. So changing one doesn't change the context. So if I go in and
change the plan, and
change this to authentication test too.. I'm saving the plan. But until I run that plan, nothing happens. So if I run the plan now, I will
get another context. We won't overwrite this one because they're separate. But what I'm going to do
is I'm going to... I nearly actually created a new ZAP context, which I don't want to do because I
want to create the plan first. So I'm going to trash that plan. And I'm going to create.. use this new
context. And again...
add the requester. And then we can go in and make sure I've copied the right URL. So put that in
there and paste URL.
So we can.. Just delete the update plan through the edits that you've done on the authentication test
now.
Yeah, I should have actually pointed out.
I could have selected the URL from the sites tree like this. But hey, I've got it saved there.
So I will save that. And we can now again go and create a new ZAP session. And then we will run the
plan. And you can see it's now created this Juice Shop context. And we're not getting the browser
being displayed because we've chosen a headless one. So we'll just have to kind of...
Let's spend a bit of time on browser and browser headless, like Chrome and Chrome headless. What
does headless stand for in the context of what we are selecting?
As you see, we don't see the browser pop up. So we don't see the Firefox or Chrome GUI. And this
means... This is really good for automation because in many cases, you're going to be running...
People run automation on a server that doesn't have a console attached to it at all and will
actually fail if you try and launch programs
that have a GUI. So headless browsers are really good for testing and automation where you don't have, you know, you don't
want things popping up all over the screen. I often use it when I'm doing something. I'm doing
a scan on one window and typing another. You just don't want all these things popping up.
Sometimes, if you're testing stuff, if you're testing authentication with the AJAX Spider,
you might want to have all these windows popping up. So you can just check,
visually, that it looks like things are logging in. But yeah. So this is why we give you that
choice. And luckily, the two main browsers support that.
So the headless option is something that browsers support in the context of
launching the browser, but not having the UI visible to the user, right?
Yeah. So our plan has run. It's successful, but we will just go to the history just to double check.
And we will see that we've made, again, two requests. One is from authentication and one is
manual. They both got the right contents and they're both 125 bytes, code 200. So everything
worked. So that's it. That is the simple case with authentication in the automation framework.
This is where we know that the ZAP...
so we browser-based authentication
works and auto-detect works as well. And as you can see, it's a lot easier than, you know,
you don't have to understand what's going on. You don't have to understand what session tokens are
used, which headers, which cookies. You don't have to worry about how to verify that the user is
logged in. ZAP handles all of that for you. It auto-detects and configures itself to handle
these things. Now, one thing you do need to be aware of is obviously things can change and you
never know. If you don't check things, you don't know what's going on. So we've already talked
about statistics, the ZAP statistics you can use to check that these things are working. And I
think we'll probably have to have a ZAP Chat session just on statistics. And we'll need to
have another session on what to do if the auto, the
authentication tester doesn't work for you. But right now, I will just stop sharing. So
we've shown you that the automation framework does support authentication. It's pretty easy
to handle as long as the authentication tester works. And if it doesn't work for you,
obviously we'll have more sessions on this, but do get in touch via the ZAP user group
because we can help you. And it's not the end of the world. ZAP will be able to handle things.
And we want to learn more about the applications that ZAP struggles with. So if there are a lot of
apps that are struggling with a particular type of authentication, we'll fix that. We will be able
to do this. We just need enough data, enough information or test cases. And then we want
this ZAP auto-detection to handle as many of the authentication cases as possible.
Amazing and insightful. Thank you, Simon.
Thank you, Yiannis.
Thank you for watching. If you like this series, then please click on the like button, subscribe
and add comments to let us know what you think of it and what else you'd like us to cover.
Thank you very much.