Hello, and welcome to another episode of ZAP Chat with myself and Yiannis.
Hello.
So last week, we talked about Google Summer of Code, and we're going to carry on talking
about Google Summer of Code, but that's going to come a bit later because we're actually
going to talk about something else first, and it's a topic for the whole of this episode,
and it's something we hope that everyone who uses ZAP will be interested in.
So this is a potential new web interface for ZAP.
So this is something we're talking about with the team, and we want to get feedback from
the community, you lot, people watching this show.
So the idea is that Google Summer of Code, as we talked about last week,
we get contributors paid by Google over the summer to work on ZAP features,
and we've had some key ZAP features implemented over the years.
So one of the projects this year we've proposed is a new web-based GUI,
and we wanted to go into that in more detail in this episode.
So kind of the first question you may have is, why do we want a new web-based GUI?
Why not stick with the GUI that we already have, right?
Exactly.
So ZAP has two GUIs already.
We've got the swing-based GUI, which is looking a little bit old,
but is very thorough and covers all of ZAP functionality.
Then we have the HUD, the heads-up display, which brings ZAP into the browser.
Now, the HUD is very innovative, and we still don't know of anything like it,
but it's proved it's not the easiest thing to maintain,
and we know some people like it, but it's not had a huge take-up.
With the swing-based GUI, we know some people do like it,
and we know some people really don't like it.
So what we've been talking about within the team is what options we have.
Now, Yiannis, do you know of any innovations in Java and GUIs recently?
Well, that was going to be my comment.
It's not that we are using swing because there's a better option out there,
and Sun and then Oracle have kind of given up on the whole evolution of web-based,
oh, sorry, swing-based features and GUIs.
So swing was designed back in the early 2000s.
It was, you know, features were being added, et cetera, et cetera,
but there isn't really a next version out there.
Okay.
There isn't a feature of UI libraries that we could be using.
And it might be old and dated, but still, Eclipse is one example, right?
The IDE is using swing.
And the problem that we had when we did the research, in answer to your question,
was that there wasn't another set of libraries or, I mean,
the only thing that came up was JavaFX, and that's been discontinued as well.
So, therefore, you have kind of stuck with this technology that's 20 years old,
still works, but has nothing to compare it with, you know,
let's say the features that we have on mobile applications or anything similar.
So I think that's really what's driving the web-based UI,
and also the element of decluttering a little bit and just picking specific
functionalities that we offer in the web-based UI.
The swing-based GUI will continue to be,
the main driver of anything that you want to do.
I think, you know, that makes sense.
And for advanced users, it's probably the one to be using.
But when it comes to the web-based UI,
there's a couple of things that we can do and do them really well
and just have a simple user interface.
So the configuration aspect, what is running,
and then also the post-mortem of that and how that is being reported
and what comes out of it.
I think...
I think overall, Simon, you described it very well.
I'm not sure about the HUD yet.
We definitely will continue to have it.
But it's so new, innovative.
And if you think about it, you know, conceptually,
the HUD is in the browser.
And effectively, you're attacking the application through the browser, right?
Yeah.
So therefore, it kind of like messes with my mind as a pentester.
It's like...
You know, is this, you know, is this a friendly or is this an enemy?
You know, like, am I hacking this or am I configuring it?
But using the browser is definitely something that we want to be using.
Here's a question for you, Simon.
So what would you put...
What would you select from the swing-based GUI?
Well, let's jump...
I'll jump back a little bit because I think you raised one very important point there,
which was the fact that we're going to carry on with the swing-based GUI.
And, you know,
why don't we just replace all of that?
Well, it's a huge job.
There's a huge number of screens, a massive amount of functionality.
And, you know, what we don't want to do is create a new web-based UI
that's a copy of the swing-based UI.
We actually have that already.
So we've got this technology called WebSwing.
So you can actually have ZAP in the browser.
But it is just the swing-based GUI in the browser.
It's really impressive.
It works really well.
But that's not what we're looking for.
You know, what we want to do is have an opportunity to think about the GUI again.
And as you were saying, Yiannis, we want to kind of think about it from very much a simplification.
We don't want to...
You know, we're not going to replace the whole swing-based GUI right now anyway.
And we don't want to just replicate what we've got.
We want a chance to think again about the UI, who's using it, and why they're using it.
And that's one reason we're having this...
This discussion in ZAP Chat, because we're very much looking for feedback from you, the people using ZAP.
So, you know, if you're a hardcore pentester who's using all the ZAP functionality,
this web-based interface isn't going to be for you, at least not for a long time.
But we know we've got a very wide range of users.
So, you know, we think there's quite a few users who use ZAP in quite a simple way,
but they're still using the desktop.
And, you know, so we're not
talking about automation here.
I mean, automation may be the end result of this,
but we're trying to think about the interface, the desktop interface,
as it's used by people who are not so experienced with ZAP
and who are not doing a full-on pentest.
So, you know, some of the things like we know a lot of people go straight to the quick scan,
the quick start pages and say, right, here's a URL, attack it.
You know, and that's...
It's using ZAP in a point-and-shoot way, which is good, but we know there are limitations.
And one of the limitations we know is feedback.
You know, there's a lot of tools out there where you just give them a URL
and they'll attack it and they'll give you the results.
But often they don't do it very effectively.
You know, there's web applications are really complex beasts.
They do so many weird and wonderful things.
So we think feedback is absolutely key.
And one of the advantages of ZAP is that even though you can use it as a point-and-shoot tool,
it's got a lot more depth.
So you can then go in and see what's actually going on
and whether ZAP is attacking your application or understanding
and attacking your application effectively.
And if it isn't, you can then configure it to do so.
It's so true.
And, you know, to be able to, you know, do a scan,
but customize the payloads or make sure authentication works
or verify that the site's tree is up to date,
even if you're using, if you're attacking a modern application.
So these are things that, you know, would serve as a good use case
for the web-based GUI, for the non-advanced, the normal user.
And also it would help drive a simple use case to conclusion
without coming in contact with the standard swing-based GUI.
So that's a
potential good candidate.
What would a bad candidate be?
Just circling back to what you were saying, Simon.
So, you know, selecting custom fuzzing payloads for parameters.
Fuzzing, yeah, no.
Let's do fuzzing on the web browser.
It's like, no, let's not.
I'm not saying we'll never do that, but at this stage,
we definitely want to look for the simple use cases.
And I think you're right.
It's finding the use cases for a particular type of user
and doing everything for them.
So if you're using ZAP in a relatively simple way,
we're looking to create a web UI that you could use
and not touch the swing-based GUI at all.
And ZAP actually runs in, you can run ZAP without the swing-based UI.
So you'd actually be able to kick ZAP off and have the web-based interface
and do whatever you want and then close ZAP down and never touch the,
never see the web, the swing-based UI.
And obviously you wouldn't have to use the web-based UI
if you're using swing.
So it's kind of, if you've got to use both,
then we've done something wrong.
You know?
You could sequence your use.
So you could fire up the web-based UI, run a basic scan and complete on it,
generate the report and then generate an automation plan, right?
Yeah, exactly.
And feed that into the standard GUI, if you like.
That makes sense.
But running that.
You know, if you're running, if we have a web-based UI to run a basic scan,
select some payloads, do automation and a little bit of authentication, right?
Then, as Simon said, as you said, right, there's no need for you to be using
the actual swing-based GUI and both of them running in parallel.
So those are the kind of use cases that we're after in terms of feedback.
It's also valid to provide feedback and say, you know,
I'm a bounty hunter and I don't envisage ever,
using a web-based GUI, fine, absolutely fine, right?
Or I'm in CI/CD, or I'm doing automation and all the tools that I use have a web-based interface and this is what it looks like, right?
So we're taking that type of feedback on board as well.
I think that's important to say, Simon, for our listeners and our viewers.
Yeah.
And we haven't, this is all in flux, so we haven't decided exactly how we're getting that feedback, but we're probably going to do a blog post on this.
And the ZAP user group is a great place to give that feedback.
Obviously there'd be comments on this YouTube video, Twitter, loads of options.
We may well do some more surveys and things, but we're kind of, yeah, it doesn't matter how you get the feedback to us, get the feedback to us and we'll collate it and go from there.
So that's the first part of this talk, this chat.
So, because what we also want to cover.
Was the actual project we're talking about, because we covered Google Summer of Code last week, but we did, we didn't go into this one in a great deal of detail and that's what we're doing now.
Now we've actually had quite a few, I want to call them students, but some of them may be students, but there's potential candidates for Google Summer of Code, quite a few get in touch already.
And actually one reason, another reason for using web-based technologies is,
there are a lot more people who can then contribute to ZAP.
You know, Java is something that is actually, you know, slowly losing its popularity.
Reckon.
Slowly,
i mean, it's going to carry on for a long time.
It's not, it's not dead yet.
I mean, look at COBOL, but we know that there are a lot of people coming along who know web-based technologies really well, better than we do in the ZAP core team, I have to say.
So this is an opportunity for those people to contribute to ZAP.
And obviously for the Google Summer of Code
it will just be
one candidate who gets chosen, but after that we expect this to
carry on, you know,
we want to carry on building on top of this GUI and we know
it's not going
to be done and dusted and never touched again once the
once the Google Summer of Code is over. So we had a few
candidates get in touch and
one of the main their main concerns is
that they don't know Java.
And in our documentation, which we showed last week, we said that we always like, you pretty
much have to contribute to ZAP in order to be considered as a serious candidate for Google
Summer of Code. And most of the easy issues on ZAP are Java related. We do have both a JavaScript
and a TypeScript project, two projects in ZAP, but they're hard. They're complicated. One of
them is the HUD and the other one is the browser add-on. They do weird things and we don't have
loads of simple bugs or features for you to implement in those. So what are we do?
Well, what we decided was we would like you to, if you're interested in contributing to ZAP and
this web-based GUI project, we would like you to create a proof of concept.
That's embedded to us. Yeah, absolutely. Through a PR request.
Yeah. Now that sounds straightforward. And one advantage of, one really good thing about ZAP is
we've got a very thorough API and that's, it supports a whole load of things. It supports
JSON. So we've got a very powerful JSON API, so you can call that. The problem is if you actually
have a separate process running on a different port, then you won't be able to call the ZAP API.
Due to cross origin request. So there are browser security features that will stop you from calling
a ZAP API. We could relax those, but we really don't want to for security reasons. It just means
ZAP is easier to attack. And we do know that people do try and attack ZAP. So what we decided
to do was create a new ZAP add-on, which is written in Java, but it allows you
to create, or allows anyone to create proof of concept web-based UIs.
So what I'll do is I will.
What I'll do, if you can share the screen and just show us this, and I think this is great because
if I look at the skillset that people use, you know, in React, right, versus the skillset that
you have as a Java developer, completely, absolutely different, right? It's a different.
Yep. So actually what I'm going to do is, so this web UI PoC,
is the PR is open, so it's not been merged yet, but it will be merged very soon. Hopefully there's
good chance by the time you watch this video, it'll be merged. And, but if we go to have a look
at this in my repos, so it's in the ZAP extensions repo, and this is my branch and we'll see,
it actually has a readme and it lend links to the web-based UI GSoC project. Now what you'll need to
do is you will need to set up a
ZAP development environment. You're going to need to do this for the project anyway. You don't need
any Java skills, but you need to set up the development environment. So we've got a link
to the developer guide. Then what you need to do is you need to install this add-on. This add-on will
not be on the ZAP marketplace. And the reason for that is we don't want people, most people
installing this, because there's a good chance there'll be security vulnerabilities in this,
you know, these are proof of concepts. So we do, you know,
is very important for the final project, but for a proof of concept, we'll be, you know,
we'll be a bit more lax about these things. So this isn't something we want people to
be running when they're using ZAP normally at this stage. And in fact, this add-on will not, well,
you can install it in the normal ZAP, but it won't work. It won't do anything interesting.
It has to be this dev version of ZAP for it to do anything interesting.
And then what you do is you point your browser at
localhost 1337. So what I actually have is I do have ZAP running. It's a dev version.
And if we go to manual explore and I have to move the zoom thing so I could actually get to
localhost 1337.
And then what we'll see is you get this very simple page saying it's the ZAP web UI
PoC Server.
And you can actually, we have a link to the ZAP API as well. So this is a web-based interface,
an existing web-based interface to the ZAP API. Now, one thing at the moment,
so let's go and have a look at say core and hosts, and we'll see
just localhost because that's the only thing we've been to. So let's just go to
example.com and then we refresh and we'll see you've got localhost and example.com.
So it really does help to explore a target application using ZAP before you start playing
around with the web UI because otherwise you won't have anything to look at.
So go back to the top level. So that's the link to the API. And what we have
is we have an example PoC. Now this one is actually implemented in JavaScript.
We're really looking for TypeScript. You can submit a PoC in JavaScript, but
TypeScript is definitely preferred, but this actually shows you how to make those requests
because we have, it's really simple. We've got the site tree here. And if you click on these
things, then you'll actually see, we can navigate around.
And if you select anything,
then you will see that we are getting the requests and find something where we get
something there, we get the response as well. So this is a really simple proof of concept
and it was done deliberately, very simple. So it's no frameworks. It's pure JavaScript,
even though it's not what we want in the end.
But it is actually making those API calls. Now, one of the key things here is
every time we expand something, we're getting a new, we're actually requesting,
we're making API requests. So I think it's important for the sites tree. The sites tree
at the moment is pretty small, but we know if you navigate over, you explore a large application,
the sites tree can get massive. And we don't want the GUI to sit there for a few seconds,
loading up the sites tree, and then handling all internally.
It's much better to make these requests and responses dynamically,
particularly as you see, these are pretty quick. You know, it's pretty snappy.
This page is talking directly to ZAP via the API. ZAP gets all the information. It's pulling stuff
out of the database or whatever, or the sites tree and returning it. So we don't think there's
a performance problem with the sites tree like this. So this is, you know,
you do want these kinds of things to be dynamic and this kind of thing shouldn't be cached.
Now, one thing we don't have at the moment is notifications, events from ZAP itself.
So this is something that we will be adding. But for the PoC, you know,
whether it'll be in place for a PoC, I don't know. We'll have to see how it goes,
but we definitely will.
A few pentesters looking at this interface would say, yeah,
this is exactly what I want, right? And it's actually, you know, it's clean, it's concise.
It gives you all the data.
It's not really an interface. I mean, by any means of TypeScript or modern standards,
it's not really an interface. Yes, it gives you the request and response. But if you're a
pentester, you shouldn't even be firing a browser to get the history of requests and responses, right?
There's a number of ways to get that. So in the concept of this PoC, it's very important to say
that we are after making sure that it has a smooth experience for the user and it's actually able to
use the ZAP APIs in a consistent way, right? In a way that gives that smooth interface view
to the user.
Yeah. And we want it to look good. We want people to enjoy using this interface.
So it's got to look good and work in the way they want it to.
So you've installed, you know, you've set up this app development environment,
and then you've installed this add-on. How can you actually add your own proof of concept?
So, what I'm going to do is just switch to the command line. Now,
I am in, because I've got a Mac, I'm in /user/Simon/Library/Application Support/ZAP_D.
Now, ZAP has a default directory that it uses and it's different on different
operating systems. If I was using standard ZAP, the release version of ZAP, it would just be ZAP
without the underscore d.
But
the underscore D and this is where ZAP puts its files and what you'll see is
there is a web UI PoC directory and there we have we've got the index the
example and you'll actually see the example is a directory. So what I'm going
to do is if you want say you want to create a new PoC proof of concept.. I'm
going to make a directory called Simon and then we go back here and go to the
top level and we'll see we now have a PoC called Simon and a click on there
it'll say 404 not found because it's just directory have a look here and
we see we've actually got an index.html. So we need an index.html. Well, if
you want to serve something from the route anyway. So, I'm just going to use
vi..
You don't have to use vi for this.. No you basically you can use whatever editor or
IDE you want and that's one reason why it's just flat, you know, very simple flat file store
use whatever you like and you know we're expecting you to come back and saying this is the tool chain
that i'm proposing. So we want those details, because we're expecting you to use the modern
frameworks, but i'm just i've just created this very text file it's not even html and refresh
and you see testing one two three and then okay we'll we're gonna go
create a very.. simple non-py script non-java script "hello world"
of index html if you ever want to know how to do this you can also watch this video.
Yep, so really simple.. Even has a header okay very exciting! Yeah, so..
i probably made a mistake there, but hopefully not and then we go back and refresh and there
we go heading one PoC hello world.
And so i mean so what you'll see is when ZAP has a server is not caching anything. So, you know, any change you make to the file store will get reflected
immediately. So you probably have to refresh the page, but what you can see is you can then very quickly create your own PoC. an what you'll then
need to do is you'll need to copy this your files back and let's go back to... here is so this
is my copy of ZAP extensions where the PR has been submitted to web UI PoC and if we go into
see if i can remember.. So, yeah, ZAP home files so src/main/zapHomeFiles/webuipoc/example.
So you would want to copy.. So to get your proof of concept working you can create the files
in this ZAP home directory and
you can play around with it get it how you like then copy those files back up to
this level so you'd create your directory at the same level as the example then you'd add all those
files and then you'd submit those to PR and you know we want you to do this. So that we can see
you submitting PRs getting feedback and then updating and i said we don't you know if you want
to call some stuff back. So that you know some really cool features that you don't want
other candidates to see
no problem you can submit those to us privately, but you know this is how we do want some one or
more PRs with functionality and so we can see that you understand this process.
I think it's a great idea to be able to have different PR requests as part of you know
showing a PoC as part of this Google Summer of Code, because it just gives you anybody can think
that they're writing, you know, some sort of javascript, typescript PoC, but to be able to
solve a UI feature, right, for a ZAP user and we know who those are based on the personas
questionnaire and we're still running that etc. is is important because when it comes to a lot
of modern web interfaces, you know. I'm thinking of like even my bank or parts of the google
website or amazon and so on there's a lot of a lot of stuff happening in the interface that's
actually not needed, right? You just need a button and the button is,
you know, something else you know it's straight out and then it has a state of its own and all
that stuff. So to be able to, you know, find the balance for the web-based UI that we will have
through PR requests and also help drive that in the future will definitely set the brain juices
of innovation running for us as a team, right as soon as we see those PR requests. Yeah. So don't
shy away from submitting your PR request. Definitely and you know for if you
do want to take part in Google Summer of Code you will need to submit a proposal which i think
ends up as so it's like a Google DOC or something ends up as a pdf and we do want to
hear about your ideas of how the interface could work, you know, the type of functionality, wireframes
how it fits together, write pretty pictures if you want, you know, example pictures of how you
think it would work. We want to get listen to your good ideas and you know the more ideas you have
the, you know, the better they are the more chance you'll have of being successful in this project.
Exactly as somebody likes to say. Yep, so i think that's it. That was all about the new web-based
UI the proposed web-based web-based UI a trip over my words now. So if you are a ZAP user use
the desktop and you don't use that many of the features then please get in touch with us
to let us know exactly what you would like us to provide and if you're thinking about
getting involved in Google Summer of Code would like to work on the web-based UI
project, then please start playing around with creating PoCs, get in touch particularly by the
ZAP developer group, if you have any questions about developing stuff for ZAP or any questions
or problems or you need new APIs created anything like that. We can help you there
and if you've got any more comments about this or any of the other episodes of ZAP Chat then
please leave them in the comments below. Thank you very much. Thank you.