Hello, and welcome to the first ZAP Chat of 2024. Happy New Year to everyone.
Hello, Happy New Year.
Here's Yiannis and myself chatting about ZAP stuff. Now, I had a quick chat and we decided that it
would be good to have a little review of 2023. So probably going to do a blog post about this as
well. So you might actually be watching this in the blog post. So you'll be able to see all the
best links. But I was just going to go through the year and we'll chat about the stuff that we got
done. What a year it has been. Very exciting year, right?
It's been a very exciting year and a very busy one. So lots got done.
January started off, we were very much focusing on authentication. So actually released the
authentication helper. It didn't have all the functionality it does now, but it allowed you to
automatically identify authentication requests and then automatically configure ZAP to handle
them. And this is something which was new for us because previously it was just like you had to
configure everything. ZAP could handle pretty much anything as long as you told ZAP how to handle it.
And in some cases you didn't know how to do that, which is kind of fair enough. So this was the
start of really getting ZAP to help you configure things more easily, particularly around authentication.
And that's something we intend to carry on through the year and hope to carry on even further.
In February, I went to OWASP AppSec Israel, where myself, Ricardo and Rick were all given
OWASP's Lifetime Achievement Awards, which is a little bit ironic given the events later on,
but those weren't taken off us. So we still got those, which is very nice to have those
recognition. But then, yeah, carry on in March and basically we're carrying on a lot more about
the authentication. So supported browser-based authentication, which I think is absolutely key
for modern web applications. We tried various things and as the Yiannis has told you, it's really
hard to authenticate to modern apps if you don't use the browser. There are some cases I've managed
to inject user sessions into a browser. You launch a browser, you inject the session and it works.
But it's very application specific and quite a few applications, I've not found a way to do it.
It is. It's even considered a security feature by some. I mean, it's not really a security feature
because of course the asynchronous JavaScript is a client-side control. So therefore, theoretically,
it cannot be trusted. Having said that, it does add a layer of obfuscation,
for the lack of a better word, when it comes to getting that valid set of jsessionid,
or .NET cookies or whatever the technology might be behind that. So it is going to be,
I think, an ever-evolving game of cat and mouse between authentication that continues to evolve.
If you look at the next versions of OAuth and so on, we've got that coming down the pipeline.
And then the security tools and ZAP at the forefront of web application and API security
tools trying to catch up with the latest authentication trends.
Yeah. And we know that authentication and automation oppose each other in some
ways because a lot of people who are doing bad things will use automation. So a lot of security
controls are there to prevent things that you need to do with ZAP if you want to automate your
security testing. So it's kind of tricky. And this is something we've always struggled with,
and it will continue to get more interesting. But we're getting there.
And the authenticating with the browser has proved very effective,
unless you use Gmail, in which case Chrome blocks you from doing that. So hey,
that's the way it goes.
I think one of the key takeaways for our listeners and learners is,
long gone are the days of you would send a get request or a post request,
and it would be a bunch of parameters. And all you have to do is to get the content length
right, and then you'd be able to, I don't know, brute force the interface.
And of course, this is not something that we're going to shy away from in the new protocols,
because overall, we have the same problem with CSRF tokens. And then it was just about generating
the sequence request. So I think it's just a case of evolving the tool set to catch up with the
client side features, for the lack of better words. I can't think of them as security control. Sorry,
I'm a bit old school there. Exactly. And I think it's important to think about, if you're developing
applications, how easy do you want to be able to test them? If you put a whole load of controls in
that make it hard to test your applications, who are you hurting? Are you really preventing
the bad people from attacking your application, or are you making their own lives harder?
So it's a balance, and that's a decision you have to make.
Yeah. And we see that a lot, actually, just to digress for a second. So in the same way that you
have
you know, the mobile space, you can check for a jailbreak on iOS, right? And there are libraries for it and
known techniques. And then typically during the retest, a jailbreak risk has either been accepted
or that feature has been included. But then during the scoping, you're like, well, I'm not going to
spend five days bypassing the jailbreak control that I told you to implement. Same with logging.
I'm not going to spend five days focusing on the logging features that I told you to implement.
In essence you end up with a set of techniques that are there in a blue team style where both sides are working
collaboratively. And surprise, surprise, you might get given a set of tokens in order to be able to
assist and get more value add out of the engagement for the company that you're actively trying to
assist their controls. Definitely. And in things like web application firewalls,
I would recommend they're turned off for a security audit, unless you want to actually test the
web application firewall, which is very valid. But if you want to test the application,
turn off the firewall so that you get as much value as possible out of those tests.
Yeah, yeah. Same with CDNs. Yeah, absolutely.
All of those things. So that was in March, we also carried on with
been doing a lot of work on the automation framework and we actually sported inline scripts,
which we haven't covered in, even though we've done quite a bit of...
Not yet, not yet.
But we will get to those definitely. And another question I asked,
on a blog post was how should we fund ZAP? And we didn't get many responses to that,
which is a shame and something that we'll come back to a little bit later in this podcast,
ZAP Chat, whatever it is. So in April, we carried on and we had authentication auto detection.
So this is where we've got a lot more implemented in the authentication helper.
So you could actually detect and configure ZAP automatically for many more cases.
And that carried on in May where we actually released the authentication automation,
the authentication tester. So very simple screen. Give us a URL, give us the credentials,
and ZAP will try and work out everything else from there. And that has proved that
there's quite a few applications which ZAP can handle all of these things for you.
Not everything, but it also collects a set of anonymized diagnostic data. So if ZAP can't
detect any part of the authentication into interaction then you can report that to us and
we can have a look at it without you having to tell us all a load of internal details you might
not want to. Yeah part of the cat and mouse game that we were just referencing for q1 continued
in q2 that was exciting. Definitely and it will carry on no doubt and in then in
actually so yeah that was april. Now may that was when we released the tester, but we also
there were some GraphQL changes some significant ones much better spidering and fingerprinting as
well. So you can actually fingerprint the different GraphQL endpoints which was very useful and we
had a change to the AJAX spider where you could exclude specific elements and that was
notable because of the sponsor development something we definitely want to see more of
so thank you to night vision for that
and we would love to do more sponsored developments where companies
pay us to implement really useful features for everyone.
Then in june more authentication so this time browser-based authentication in the AJAX spider
and this was absolutely key because as we mentioned before it's so hard to inject a session
into a browser and in many cases it's not possible. So this meant that you could launch
the AJAX spider which is
one of our key ways of at the moment it's the only way to explore modern web applications in
automation and this allowed you to handle it in authentication which you know we had some blog
posts about things like juice shop. Juice shop was one of the few applications i was able to
inject the session so we're basically running selenium scripts in when we launch the browser
and go okay we've got this session token and we'll put it in the is it local storage or
session storage one of those and then refresh the page and it then gets logged in
so you can then explore the application effectively through the browser, but that's unusual.
So browser-based authentication with the AJAX spider is particularly effective and talking of
selenium we actually supported selenium 4 which was very good so we we updated to handle that.
It's always interesting with significant frameworks when they have new releases and you go
"okay it's so much better but there's lots of changes we've got to". All the previous api selenium
i have a habit of doing that i remember it's going to show my age, but like selenium one right and it's
like what happened to all the 0.9 api calls? It's like no not there okay cool yeah and you've
got to like rewrite all those things but it's part of the the trade and supporting right and..
Exactly, yeah! ..you've got to do it. Yeah have to do these things and you know we had a lot of problems
with networking layer before that got rewritten to use a more modern library. So we we these are just
of the cost. We also started releasing the docker images on the
github container registry. Which is particularly useful as docker hub started charging quite
significant non-trivial amounts of money if you're pulling lots of images and we had we were able to
announce two google summer of code projects one on importing postman definitions and the other one
the browser recorder. Which was really great and those completed later on in the year.
July, not much happened on the out on the outside but there's a lot going on behind the scenes
a lot which we announced in august which was the move from OWASP to the software security project.
So this was a really big significant change for us and this comes back to funding.
We have found that we need to have people working full-time on ZAP it's such a significant project
there is so much going on and we've got a lot of volunteers which is great
and volunteers do really useful things but we need people working full-time
and i've been able to work full-time on ZAP thanks to a couple of startups, but
those relationships have not been have not proved to be easy to maintain. So it's quite a cost for a
startup and we found we can't rely on them. So what we've done we've joined the software security project
and we were able to get temporary funding for myself and ricardo to work full-time
on ZAP and that is that's the reason we moved. You know we are actually some of us are still both
myself and rick are still OWASP project leaders so we still take part in OWASP we sort of contribute
to OWASP but the ZAP project is now part of ssp which is part of the linux foundation.
It's really important to just reflect on that for a second and there's no diss to OWASP right and the great work
that is happening at the open web application security project and has been happening for a number of years. The the i remember
having this debate when log4j hit right a few years back that december and just listening to
you simon right now just go through the roadmap right there are a number of non-startups like
significant companies with massive revenues you know vested share options all that kind of stuff.
That have a less impressive roadmap of delivery for 2023 than ZAP has yet there is the expectation
because the project is you know open source and part of the open web application security
project and so on that it will have such a you know progressive roadmap. That has these
aggressive elements authentication and some of the other things that we talked about yet no one
is willing to do the checks on the funding and when people back in that december where
dissing you know the apache software foundation with regards to the maintenance of log4j given the
black hat talk in 2016 on log4j. It was like hold on like how much money do you think the apache
software foundation like accumulated throughout the course of these five years and if you do the
math it's trivial compared to the amount of you know big companies financial organizations. So on
that use these
libraries and take them for granted right. So at some stage i think this whole world of
open source software that is worthy you know to be up there with roadmaps as impressive as those of ZAP
need to have that relevant backing. So i think it's only logical that you guys moved and
that is the next step of the evolution of ZAP and perhaps there's another one after that, right?
I completely agree
and it's not just a ZAP problem as you said it's a problem
across a lot of open source projects and ZAP started off as a
a little project for me to try and help teach myself about web security and it just also felt
wrong there wasn't that open source project out there and you know we're competing whether we like
it or not against commercial companies who have hundreds of employees doing the same thing that
we're doing with two employees at the moment and a lot of volunteers.
So it's challenging, and I'm not expecting to have 100 people working for me.
It would be great, but that's not going to happen.
But just having two of us working full-time on ZAP has made a huge difference,
and I'd love to grow that, but somehow we've got to work out the funding,
and we haven't done that yet.
We've got temporary funding, but, yeah.
I think it's coming down the road, right?
We're working on it.
If you're having 100 employees, so, you know, there's stuff in the works,
so not to be, you know, depressing our audiences in January.
Yeah, completely agree.
And the other thing we did in August was we released a new developer focus questionnaire.
What do you want us to focus on?
Because, you know, we want to make sure that we're focusing on the things
that make a difference to you.
And thank you
to everyone, who filled that in
it was really useful.
In August, we also added support for file transfers in the API.
That's something a lot of people have been asking for,
and that was only available in the core, so it was only available in the weeklies.
But that was, you know, one of the – we were able to do some developments,
even though there was a lot of stuff going on in the background.
And then in September, we carried on working, really working towards 2.14,
the next big release.
And we –
the Google Summer Code students finished,
so both of them completed their project successfully and wrote blog posts on them,
and both of them carried on contributing, which is really great.
And very importantly, we started the ZAP Chat series.
So September is when we started that, and this is actually the 13th episode.
Not unlucky for some, hopefully.
So, yeah, 13 episodes now.
So we've kept going.
And thank you, Yiannis, for keeping on prompting me and saying,
what are we going to do next week?
What are we going to do next week?
And again, okay.
Thank you for your pictures as well.
No, it's been fun.
It's been fun.
It's been great to see – you know, I remember the one OWASP project, right,
where tools – the offensive tool set was so much more basic and rudimentary.
And just seeing the great work that you guys are doing with ZAP
to be able to help showcase some of that, you know, it's been a pleasure.
Absolute delight.
And actually, I mean, the reason you got involved was the suggestion of zapIt,
this new reconnaissance scan.
Which we released in October, along with 2.14.
So 2.14, very big release for us.
We're trying to – we're kind of managing two releases a year,
which means I forgot to mention 2.13.
We must have done that earlier in the year.
Oh, well, that's one of those things.
So we did 2.13, so we did two releases this year.
One of the two releases in 2023.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
So that was October.
And in November, quite a lot of – you know,
of focus on documentation videos so a lot more on how to handle modern web applications
authentication with documentation videos around that and we started doing a lot of videos around
the automation framework as well. Which we will carry on we've got many more of those to do.
Many jobs are waiting in the pipeline thanks Ricardo. Yep definitely and then in december
obviously december's often a bit of a quiet month um but still a lot going on and you know we are
really we published the results of the development focus questionnaire. So the top things were
handling modern web apps which is one of our key focuses authentication automation those two are
right up there. Then the next ones were ease of use and manual testing and those five were there
wasn't a huge difference between them it wasn't so you know those are the the big five really.
And the ease of use one is interesting because it's something we haven't really been able to
focus on and we know that the ZAP desktop gui has kind of drifted a bit and hasn't had much love
so one of the things that Yiannis put together was the user persona questionnaire. Well, with the
help of the team right i've been doing by myself and it's more about asking the question of like
"Who are the users of ZAP
in the context of the future releases?"
So that we can start decluttering the user interface
and potentially get into a flow state
where you go from left to right or cycles
or clockwise, anticlockwise,
whatever the theme might be in the wireframes.
And I think what triggered this for me is
there's a number of features, for example,
when you do automation, right?
Where you click a tiny button, the plus sign,
to add a plan, right?
And all of a sudden, a whole world appears.
It's as if you've opened a door to a new dimension.
It's like, oh, right, this is cool.
Had I not clicked on this tiny little button, right,
would I know that all this is there?
Yeah, we got to the stage
where ZAP was getting more and more cluttered.
So we then tried to hide things.
And that means you might, it looks a bit complicated,
but you might think that's it, and it's not.
There's loads more.
We were talking about
how we thought, well, what about this user?
And what about this user?
And we were kind of thinking, well,
do we really know who's using ZAP
and how they're using it?
And the answer was no.
So many people just download ZAP
and don't get in touch with us, which is fine.
But then it's very difficult for us to go,
right, these are the types of users,
you know, we've got these types of users
and they use ZAP in this way,
so we need to make it better for them.
So this questionnaire is really important to us
because this is the start of us going,
who is using ZAP and what do you want out of it?
And then how can we make it better for you?
And that will be, you know,
that's definitely the desktop GUI,
but there might be other things as well
and might be new features.
There's a whole range of things that will come out of this.
And I'm expecting many more questionnaires as well
as we kind of delve into who's using it?
What are you using it for?
You know, we need to know that in order to make it better.
Because we keep saying, you know,
we've had feedback.
We've had feedback saying the GUI looks outdated
or it's not very good.
It's like, yeah, we kind of know that,
but what do we do about it?
We need very specific things.
And it could be just things about this button is too small
or it could be complete rework of the flow of the application.
So there's, yeah, just telling us it's no good
is helpful, but only so far.
We need to know a lot more
and that's what we're doing with these questionnaires.
Absolutely.
And just,
you know, just to give a perspective, right?
It's very different what a good GUI will look like
to a pentester or a red teamer.
Yeah.
This is a bugbounty hunter versus somebody running it
as part of automation in CI/CD versus somebody in operations, right?
It's just a different, completely different style of flow based on,
you know, who we are in cybersecurity related fields.
So if you give a really good GUI
to the pentest community, you risk alienating the ops people,
CI/CD, and those who are in the trenches with development teams.
If you do the opposite, right, and you give a really good GUI
to bugbounty hunters, you're probably going to alienate,
you know, some of the pentest folk out there
because they're not after hunting, you know, the tick SQL injection.
They're after hunting very specific bespoke things as part of,
you know, penetration testing.
So,
that is where the whole concept of decluttering the GUI
goes back to as an origin, and that's where we need your assistance.
And if I'm not mistaken, Simon, the questionnaire is still open, right?
It is.
Yeah, we still want more.
We've had a lot of responses.
Thank you all who have responded.
But if you haven't, please let us know.
And some people have said they actually like the GUI.
So if we then went and changed everything to work in a completely different way,
we'd piss off those people.
So, you know, it's hard.
It's okay.
We do hard things, but we need to make sure we change things in a way
that makes it better for as many people as possible.
So if you want, if you want your views to be counted,
please fill in that questionnaire and it's on the front of zaproxy.org.
And we're nearly out of time.
But one thing I wanted to talk about was 2024 and what's coming next.
And we kind of mentioned that, you know,
you've told us what the development focuses should be,
and those are the things we're focusing on. To be fair,
there were things we thought were important anyway, and we're focusing on.
So, but definitely those are where our main focus will be.
But the other one which I've kind of mentioned before is funding.
And I kind of think this is going to be the make or break year for ZAP,
because we need to work out a way of funding,
which means we're not relying on a couple of companies or individuals.
And we've talked about various things. We've got various options.
But, you know, we haven't solved it yet.
We haven't got the money coming in and, but we still want,
we believe in open source and we want to make sure that ZAP is available to as many people as possible.
And that's, you know, our aim is to make the Internet that little bit more secure for everybody.
And we believe there should be an open source project like ZAP providing these capabilities.
And if it means we're not as well funded as some
companies with a load of VC funding, that's the way it goes.
You know, we know that. But we think ZAP is providing a huge amount of benefit to the industry.
So how does the industry fund projects like ZAP?
And that's a key question.
And the two are not orthogonal, right?
This is not a, just to be very clear to our audience,
this is not an attempt to say, you know, we're going to close the source or we're going to like start licensing everything to death or anything like that.
That's not the objective. The objective is to be able to do
what other open source projects have done very successfully in the benefit of, you know, the community
in essence. The fact that we have to developers who are partially funded,
full time, though. But partially funded through a mechanism.
That is not sustainable. Egers the question,
how do we make this sustainable and grow that development team more?
So this is not an attempt to, by any means,
completely
monetize ZAP and you know take over the world by introducing license fees only
close source everything. No, what we are trying to do is find that balance in 2024 whereby you ask
for a feature it gets delivered but the people that deliver it are actually compensated for their
work right that's the the objective as a bunch of other open source projects have managed to do.
Yeah so if you have any ideas about that or if you'd like to donate large sums of money to us
or any sums of money to us. Please get in touch as a our focus is definitely going to be on
new features and modern web applications, authentication, automation ease of use and
manual testing as well you know those are you know those are and but we do need to
know you know who is using ZAP and how you're using it so that user persona questionnaire is
really key. So please fill that in and other than that have a great 2024 and we will carry on with these
and probably get back to the automation framework we'll have to have a chat about what we're going
to talk about next but stay tuned. Absolutely and happy new year everyone. May all your shells
return root as we used to say and that doesn't only mean the cyber world but in life too.
Happy new year folks! Thanks for watching bye.