Hello, and welcome to another episode of ZapChat with myself, Simon, and Yanis.
Hello!
Great, so last week we covered spiders, both the traditional spider and the Ajax spider.
So hopefully today we're going to get on to ActiveScan, but before we do that, we've got a couple of little jobs.
Now, one of them I already mentioned, which was the PassiveScan weight.
But I'm going to demo it this time just so you can see why you really want to use it.
So let's share my screen.
While you do that, Simon, just to say that a delay job is one of the easiest jobs to implement in often distinguishing between tasks.
Not only does it give you the opportunity to let a previous job finish and complete and so on and so forth,
but also it just gives you that sanity check that everything up until that point has run according to plan,
because it is a set of jobs that are part of a plan.
So very important to incorporate delays in your overall strategy when it comes to automation.
Exactly.
So what I'm going to do is I am going to...
I'm going to switch to the automation tab because we're still on the automation framework and I'm going to create a new plan.
And what we're going to do is we're going to run the spider and I'm going to run the report.
So we're not going to go into the report in detail, but I want to show you something.
So to start with, we have to actually put a URL in.
What are we scanning this week?
I'm going to go back to...
It's just nice and easy.
Good call.
So local host budget.
And we're just going to spider it.
And then we're going to run the report.
And the report I'm going to use is the traditional PDF report.
And for demoing purposes, I'm going to display the report.
This may come up on my other screen.
I'll just move it across.
But let's run that and see what happens.
So the spider should be pretty quick.
And there's the report.
And actually, this one did come up with some alerts, which is not what I expected.
There may be low risk and information.
Oh, no.
There's three mediums as well.
Yeah.
So I tried this just now.
Let me try that again to see if we get anything different or whether it's going to just kind of mess it up.
That's better.
That's what I was expecting.
So this is a timing thing.
So basically, ran the spider and generated a report.
The first time, as you saw, we did actually get some alerts.
This time, we've got none at all.
So why did that happen?
What happens is we're getting alerts from passive scanning.
So passive scanning happens in the background.
And we have a set of background threads.
And so the spider is completely abandoned.
The spider goes ahead, does its job, explores BUDGET, finishes.
We run the report job.
And then it's kind of a timing thing.
How far has the passive scanner got?
First time, it found a few things before we ran the report.
The second time, it hadn't had a chance to get started.
So this is why you need a delay job.
Now, we could have got a generic delay job.
But we also have a very specific one, which we have talked about before and demoed before.
And so that is the passive scan weight.
So I'll add that.
And you see we've got that.
It's just got one parameter, which is a max duration.
If you leave it at zero, it will wait until the passive scan is finished.
But if you've got a particularly large site and you want to make sure it finishes in a certain period of time, you might want to set that.
So this is in minutes.
You might say, OK, we just want to wait for a minute, five minutes, whatever you want.
But if you finish the passive scan weight before the passive scan is finished, you might miss out on some alerts, as happened.
Now, why are we adding a passive?
So what's the advantage of adding the passive scan weight versus a traditional delay job?
So in this case, we know when the passive scan will finish.
So if we actually, if we, so say we say we want a max duration of one minute.
Well, if the passive scanner finished before then and we used a traditional delay job,
then we'd still wait for that minute.
Whereas in this case, it'll take a few seconds.
So let's run this.
I will just clear the session again.
So we're starting from scratch.
We've got no alerts down here.
Run that.
For our new listeners and viewers, you know, you don't have to clear the session every time.
We're doing that so that you see a clean log and sequence of events.
So here's the report.
Yep.
So we found the medium, low informational and average.
If we have a look down here, the passive scan weight took two seconds.
So we'd put a delay in for a minute.
We'd be waiting for a minute with no reason.
So that's the advantage for our listeners, right?
So the passive scan weight waits for the passive scan to complete while otherwise with a delay job,
you would be guessing seconds or minutes or whatever the time period might be.
Exactly.
Now, there are two reasons that I can think of why you want the passive scan weight.
The traditional one is before you run the report.
So that we know that the passive scanner is finished and picked up all of the alerts, passive scan alerts.
The other one we did cover in the last session with the spiders because we've got a special alert for detecting modern web apps.
And so if you actually want to use a traditional spider and then only use the Ajax spider,
if the traditional spider spots is a modern web app, then you'll also need the passive scan weight in between those two spiders.
Why do you need the passive scan weight between those two spiders?
Because it's a passive scan which detects whether something is a modern web app or not.
So again, if you run the traditional spider, we still might have not gone through all of the passive scan might have finished.
It might have detected it's a modern web app.
We'll go, it's not modern.
We'll carry on when in fact it is.
We just need to wait for that passive scan to finish.
You need to let the passive scan complete in order for the report to be generated correctly.
For the finding that a modern web app has been spotted here.
And if you don't do that, you risk having the same way that here we've got the passive scan weight.
You risk having this spider complete.
But then you haven't completed running all the passive scan rules against that rule set.
So that's why you need the passive scan weight for in between spidering and also in between spidering and reporting in this case.
Exactly.
So that's the passive scan weight.
But we do have another option.
So let me just get rid of some of these because we don't want to show we don't need any of these.
And we don't even need the spider.
Because what we're going to show is the delay job.
So that's down here.
Now, I'll start off just by running it showing.
So you've got an option.
You've got either time or file name.
I'm going to just leave it blank.
And run it.
And we'll see.
It does nothing.
What's the difference between time and file name?
Let's have a look.
So let's put a delay or we'll put time of five.
Now, this is it's not a spinner.
You can put anything you like in here.
But the format expected is actually hours, minutes, seconds.
So you can put that in or you can put that in.
So five seconds.
So five second delay.
And let's run that.
And we'll see it's running two, three, four, five.
There we are.
Okay.
Now, then let's have a look at the file.
So I'm going to clear that.
And what I'll do is a file I'm going to put in is this one.
So actually just switch to.
The terminal and.
File not found.
Great.
So I'm going to.
Save that and.
Run.
And.
That shouldn't have happened.
I think that the main point that you were trying to display here was that if
you point to a file that does not exist.
Then by default.
Of course, the delay is going to be invalid.
Right.
That's not going to be.
Functioning correctly.
Yeah.
The delay.
Thank you for pointing out.
Basically.
We need a time in there.
So it's whichever of these happens first.
So.
If I just put in the five seconds there.
And it's kind of chooses either.
So we'll wait for five seconds.
And then.
That will finish.
So what I wanted to do.
Well, I should have meant to do.
That.
I'm going to do.
Okay.
So it looks like.
I've already done that.
The delay was put in five hours.
So.
That will.
Then we doesn't.
That matters.
If we run that.
Then that's just going to sit there.
So.
Video.
It's been on video.
I think we're going to run out of time on zoom.
So what I can do is we go back to the terminal.
So we saw that the file.
Oh, oh.
DM.
LS.
Would have helped.
That file doesn't exist.
What I'm going to do now is.
I can do.
I'm going to do.
going to do now is I am just going to touch it and for those who don't know
Linux commands this will just create an empty file call that name and you keep
an eye on the running task and then you'll see it finishes so what this
means is we can run the task this delay job until that file exists now why would
you want to do this well this the standard use case we're thinking of is
where you have a set of unit tests that explore your application thoroughly all
fairly well and they actually use a browser or the network tests so
integration tests typically and what you can do is you can proxy these through
zap and this is a really great way of helping zap explore your application
effectively because often you know if you've got a good set of integration
tests then you'll have
good data in there the more you the better data zap has the better zap can
explore the application and the better zap can test it but if you're running
that integration test those will be run completely outside of zap so zap
doesn't know how long they're running for and this is what the delayers job
is for so you can say okay it's gonna take 20 minutes to run the tests we'll
put a delay in for 20 minutes or 25 minutes just to be safe but sometimes
you know you don't know exactly how long so you could say okay
you don't have to worry about delaying for a certain time and go okay run the
tests create a file something that's that can at the zap can access and then
it will be fine however we've got some other options as well so what I do is
switch back to switch to the proxy org and we go to documentation and we then
have automate and the automation framework and it'll be set up quite quickly and then I'm going to log into the program and it's all set up nicely.
scroll down you can see all of the jobs here and we're building up that set of videos that we're
recording now and then we've got the delay job and you'll see it's got those parameters so it
explains about the time but it also says there's a couple of other options so we can either call
a static method or we can call the API endpoint. Well actually while I'm here I will just run this
again and we'll see it finishes really quickly and that's because the file still exists so I'm
just going to take that file off and we will then run it and it's not going to finish for five hours
which yeah well so let's have a look at these options. One of them is a static method now that
is something that we can call within ZAP so if we go into scripts and we will cover scripts in more
detail another time so I can create a new script and delay and we will use oh scroll I'm not going
to use a template it's a standalone script and what I need to do is call this method
copy and paste and once again so have a look down here we can see the delay job is still running
and there you go it's finished so we can call that directly but that you've got to actually be
within ZAP to be able to do that so let's switch back and we can see we can call an API endpoint as
well so let's kick this off again and paused and we now go to the browser and we point the browser
at ZAP
then this is the default page you'll get if you point at the host and port that ZAP is listening
on got a local API and so this is a UI which allows us to just navigate around automation
and we've got this end delay job now I've turned off the API key to make it easy and I'm in a safer
environment if you're not in a safer environment then you want to set an API key and you want to
provide it so you have to set an API key and you want to provide it so you have to set an API key
right absolutely but we have a look here so that job is running and we run the end API job and you'll
see it's finished so that means we've got an option for pausing the ZAP plan while you're
doing other things typically proxying stuff through your application to help ZAP explore it
more you know more thoroughly and then you can finish the job and carry on with a plan and you've
got the option of just using the ZAP plan to do that and then you've got the option of just
using the ZAP plan to do that and then you've got the option of just using a pure timer based thing
you can use a file name you can use a ZAP API call internal call or a ZAP API call and you can
think of anything else that we should support and we don't let us know you know we can add these
things it's a really good set of options and what I like about this is that it demonstrates how
dynamic automation actually is right because you're relying on another file to be created
or you're relying on an API call to terminate something that's going to take five hours to
run so it's really good to see all those options come together on the excuse of just you know a
passive scan weight and how to best evolve that in the context of automation exactly cool so now
the what we're going to cover is the active scan job so this is where we're actually going to
attack things so I'm going to carry on using budget and what I'm going to do I've got rid of
the delay jobs because we're not interested in those and I'm just going to
add the active scan job which is right towards the end and you'll see it's got quite a few
options but I'm just gonna use it like that and we will start a new session so we've got no alerts
down here and I will run that and it finishes really quickly and it finds nothing now this is
because we have a kind of separation of duties the active scan job is going to be a little bit more
complicated than the active scan job and the active scanner only attacks things it doesn't
do exploring at all we've already covered all the different exploring options we've got in previous
videos so we've got we can import APIs we can run the spiders we've talked about proxying tests
through zap that is how you explore the applicant your application but lots of options and you have
to explore it before you can actually attack it so running the active scan job on its own
will do nothing so in order to demo it we will actually have to explore and because we're just
using budget we can use the traditional spider now you'll see that we automatically put that
when you add jobs we have to automatically put them where we think they're going to be useful
in this case it's right but say you're adding a the passive scan weight job and you wanted
it between the two spiders you have to move it yourself now I'm not going to run it like this
because it'll take a while and we don't you don't really need to to watch to see it sitting
there spinning so what I'm going to do is talk about the options that we've got with the active
scan job now we only have one context at the moment and we don't have any authenticated users
as I've mentioned we're going to cover those in a future video the policy we can actually have scan
services so you can define policies which cover different sets of rules and I wasn't going to demo
those now but I will show how you can actually change the default policy but you can within zap
you can define your own policies which say only look for cross-site scripting or something like
that only look for SQL injection only look exactly injection right that's where the default policy
needs to be overridden for only a set of rules to be included as part of your custom policy and you
know so if you're doing a
scheduled scan once a week or overnight you might want to have most of the rules enabled but if
you're doing a scan as part of CICD you might say okay I only want process scripting or something
like that enabled you might want to tie it down very tightly so that it runs much more quickly
so we have a an option here for the maximum time any one particular rule will run in minutes and
then we have the maximum time
that the whole scan will take so these are separate things and these are all options that
are standard within zap if you're using it as a desktop tool and we've got the maximum number of
alerts per rule now this is quite useful if you're actually scanning a large application and say
you've got you know say you're missing a particular header if you're missing a header security header
on all of the pages you could get tens hundreds
thousands of alerts potentially so what you can do is you can actually say I only want 10 alerts
you know if you know that well you're going to get a certain number of alerts and after that it makes
no difference you know if you know that they're missing on most of your web pages that the security
headers you don't need to you don't need to look for every single one and what the maximum alerts
per rule means is that after say we set that to 10 then after we found 10 alerts for a particular
rule we will stop that rule running so this will speed up your scan
but I'm also gonna we also have default thresholds and strengths so the threshold is the level at
which the scan rules report potential vulnerabilities if you've got a low
threshold this means the alerts are the rules are more likely to report vulnerabilities you've got
a high threshold it means they're less likely to report them so putting it low means you probably
get more more alerts and putting it high means you probably get less alerts now normally we think
we we would assume most people would keep the default threshold on medium except unless you
want to actually turn all these rules off by default and that's how you can do it by the
threshold so this is a kind of a you can change the threshold say okay we want more type of alerts
or less you may maybe you want to have the high threshold because it's automation you want to make
sure that it's
your developers just see things which are much more likely to happen but the other option is
turning everything off then you can turn specific rules on so when it comes to threshold I often
parallelize threshold with you know the indicative first initial risk that a rule has right so for
example SQL injection where you enter a tick character and you get a SQL error back that
would typically fall in the default threshold of high
right because it's very likely that indeed you have some sort of SQL breaking at the back end it
might not be completely injectable it might be blind Etc but there's something going on which
is a high risk regarding the web app or you know API endpoint exactly you're attacking now with
that in mind what strength how do we how do we define strength in the context of the default
policy so strength so both thresholds and strength are actually per rule
so and these are then the default policy applies to all of the rules you're running and by default
zap will run the active scanner will run all of the rules you've got installed so and the strength
is very much it kind of comes down to how many requests app sends or how many requests the rule
sends so the the kind of finger in the air we have is with a low strength we will aim to send at most
about half a dozen requests
parameter per page so that it doesn't sound like very many but that builds up pretty quickly over
a larger web app right exactly so medium is around a dozen so around 12 10 to 12 and not all rules
will do this so for something like cross-site scripting what we do is we send a safe value
first and we see whether it's reflected anywhere in the page and if it's not we try something else
but generally cross-site scripting will only send
a few initial payloads and without will then carry on even if you put it on really high strength
it'll only do a couple of payloads and if it doesn't find anything reflected it will carry on
but it's all it's very much specific to each individual rule so your medium is around 10 to 12.
I 20 to 24 and then we've got an insane level and the insane level basically says the rule can send
as many requests it like it could be hundreds and in a couple of cases I think it is hundreds
so
we don't expect people to use insane strength for all rules on a large application it'll just take
too long yeah so it's much it's much more this is for you know manual pen testing you found one
particular page and you're really suspicious about it you haven't been able to tie down
exactly put it on insane strength on one particular rule hammer it and see you know have a really good
go but in this case leave it on minimum medium and this means
again the active scan job will do nothing at all because I've turned the default rules off
so we've got policy rules and this is where we can have exceptions for default policy
and so what I'm going to do is we can add any rule we like and I'll go for cross-site scripting
reflective and you can see the threshold by default is off which won't help unless of course
the default threshold is on in which case you will want to turn particular rules off potentially so I'm
going to switch that to medium and that means we have one rule set on medium uh all everything
else is off and I'm not specified well I've got 10 maximum of 10 alerts but that shouldn't matter
and we'll now run that and you see the spider finishes pretty quickly and there we go the
active scanner has finished and we do actually have a fine text yeah scripting and that looks
pretty convincing to me
yeah so that is the active scan job now basically if you have you can choose to
whichever policy you like but we've also got some Advanced Options as well judges go through
very quickly we have a delay in milliseconds now usually we have this complaint that
tools like zap take too long when doing active scanning
well sometimes
okay
too quick and it actually hammers web applications we've had lots of cases where either web
applications fall over or if you've got some sort of firewall in there detecting things coming in
too quickly and then blocking the scanner so yeah so we can actually put a delay in
milliseconds for every in between every request that zap sends so this will slow zap down and
might mean your your application actually stays up or that you know the firewall doesn't kick in
we also have the number of threads per host now this defaults to the number of cores so I've got
16 this will speed things up but it will also put more strain on your system you can shift up to 32
will be quicker but you know whether you're the host or the the box running zap might struggle
then or we can drop the number of threads down but then that will take longer
so we have a few a safe option on on threads is to go up in not powers of two right because you
know 16 32 64 128 that's a large thread pool you tend to go up in increments of two instead of the
power of two and of course always test 16 threads per host per rule is a lot right by default as
well so 32
is twice that maybe you need a value somewhere in between and it's best to test these things out
instead of just guessing and you know multiplying the value exponentially exactly now we have the
active scanner's lots of options we've just exposed a few of them by the automation framework
job the ones we think are most useful there's an option to add a query parameter handles anti-csf
tokens which I think we do by default inject a
plug-in id so this actually injects a header saying which rule is running so you can actually
use this as a way of detecting what caused problems on the back end or something like that you'd tie
in with the logs or something like that and we've got an option to scan all headers by default we
just attack a small set of headers you may want to actually you know if you really want to do a
thorough test scan all headers but this will take longer there's always a balance of what do you
actually attack versus what you're actually attacking and what you're actually attacking
this is how long things take the more you attack the longer it'll take the more chance of actually
finding potential vulnerabilities just one last comment on injecting plug plug-in ids from me
very useful if you know that you're up against the WAF and you want to make sure that you are
actually bypassing that so when you've got the opportunity you can enter the plug-in id regex
and we've got those in the documentation pages and what does that mean it means that you're not
actually you know doing its job but you're testing the application this can stand up to
scrutiny and you're allowing those plug-in headers to go through because they're white listed on the
web application file exactly or if you say you want a particular key to get through the firewall
and maybe that's how it's configured then in that case we'd use the replacer job to actually
add a one specific header to all requests so we've got a range of options and so we can do
that as well so if you need to do something that's more sophisticated then you could actually
add a script which is also supported by the automation framework and that will cover in a future episode
there you go yes indeed we've got the replacer job that's good inspiration for the next video
we've done the replacer job already so for a bigger script right not just the here's the
scripts are definitely up there have to work out we haven't done the reports job yet
we've done most we've done most of the standard work
we've done most of the standard work
ones uh we'll have to go through but there's still yeah scripting and authentication so those
are a couple of big ones which whether we'll do them all in those in one session i don't know but
we'll see how we get on so that's everything for this episode if you like these videos then
please will like them on youtube and subscribe and add comments saying what else you'd like us
to cover thank you very much and until next time bye now